<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Speculum matricis hybernicum, or, The Irish midwives handmaid catechistically composed by James Wolveridge, M.D. ; with a copious alphabetical index.</title>
            <author>Wolveridge, James, d. 1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 120 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15116</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12255699</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12255699</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57430</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57430)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 161:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Speculum matricis hybernicum, or, The Irish midwives handmaid catechistically composed by James Wolveridge, M.D. ; with a copious alphabetical index.</title>
                  <author>Wolveridge, James, d. 1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[54], 166, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Okes, and are to be sold by Rowland Reynolds ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing lists imprint as Printed for Rowland Reynolds.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Obstetrics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Childbirth --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:1"/>
            <p>SPECULUM Matricis Hybernicum; OR, THE <hi>IRISH MIDWIVES</hi> HANDMAID. Catechiſtically Compoſed, BY JAMES WOLVERIDGE, <hi>M. D.</hi> With a Copious Alphabetical Index.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN <hi>IV Xta MagnaLIa DeI sCrIptor,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Anno Domini, 1669.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chronogramma,</hi> 1669.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Damnoſa quid non imminuit dies?</l>
               <l>Aetas parentum, pejor avis, tulit</l>
               <l>Nos nequiores, mox daturos</l>
               <l>Progeniem vitioſiorem.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Horat. Lib. 3. Carminum, Ode 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Okes;</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Rowland Reynolds,</hi> at the Kings-Arms in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE AUTHOR</hi> TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT may perhaps be wondred, why the Author ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Book, not only to be toſſed by the impetuous waves of the Iriſh Seas (e're it could ſet foot on the Engliſh-ſhore) but more to be admired, that he ſhould expoſe it to be tumbled, and ſearched by the Accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Ingenious Cenſure, and
<pb facs="tcp:57430:3"/>ſcrutiny, not only of Learned Scholars, but of Grave Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, and Expert Midwives. Since alſo it is manifeſt, that very many have not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed their Oyle, but their Ink upon this Subject; It may not only be accounted Arrogancy and Preſumption, but imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent folly, and improfitable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours in the Author; either to think to out-do former Writers; or in his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt to be wiſer than the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Readers, ſo as to out-do the one, or out-wit the other. Aſſuring you, therefore, that his aim is at neither, he hopes it will be candidly received by all. Though the Title-Page
<pb facs="tcp:57430:3"/>may arrive your view in an Iriſh Garb,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricis;</hi> or the Iriſh Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, &amp;c.</note> with her Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid bare-foot, and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legg'd; or at the beſt, in Brogues and Kerchers, (according to the Cuſtome of the Countrey;) yet, be aſſured, It hath an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh dreſs under an Iriſh man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; it being never intended for the Iriſh, (though I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh it may be ſerviceable to them alſo, if occaſion be,) whoſe fruitfulneſs is ſuch, that there is ſcarce one barren a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; and whoſe har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, and facility in bringing forth, is generally ſuch, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther requires the nice Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of diligent, vigilant Nurſe-keepers, or the Art of
<pb facs="tcp:57430:4"/>expert Anatomiſts, or the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied pains and skill of dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Midwives; being, more like the Hebrew women,<note place="margin">Exod. Cap. <hi>1.</hi> Ver. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> than the native Aegyptians; deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the Midwives can come to them. And that this truth may gain the more Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit; mind a Story related by as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Harvey, de Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione Anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, <hi>Chap.</hi> de Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu <hi>Page 276. An Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</hi>
               </note> Learned a Phyſitian as our Age hath known; who reports it (as he ſaith) from the mouth of the Lord <hi>Carew,</hi> Earl of <hi>Tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and Lord Preſident of <hi>Munſter,</hi> for many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; who alſo wrote the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of thoſe times. The Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is this; There was an Iriſh Woman, wife to a Common Souldier, who, though big with
<pb facs="tcp:57430:4"/>child, accompanied her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in the Camp; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Army daily was in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, marching from place to place; it hapned, that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a ſudden flood after a haſty rain, a ſmall Brook began to ſwell ſo high, that it hindred the Armies marching for one hour: In which time of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies halting, the womans pains of child-bearing came upon her; inſomuch, that ſhe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing her ſelf to the next thicket of ſhrubs (without the help of any Midwife, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preparation of Baby-clouts) there, all alone, brings forth Twins; (whom God ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeing in their blood,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Cap. 16. Ver. 5.6.</note> ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:57430:5"/>unto them, live, when no eye pityed them;) both which ſhe brought down to the River preſently, and there waſhed both her ſelf, and them; which done, ſhe wraps them up (not ſwadled at all) in a courſe Iriſh mantle, and carries them at her back, marching with the Army the ſame day barefoot &amp; bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legg'd (as ſhe was) twelve miles, and that without the leaſt prejudice to her health, or to the lives of her children. The next day after, it pleaſed the Lord Deputy <hi>Montjoy,</hi> (who at that time commanded the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt the Spaniard, who had beſieged <hi>Kinſale</hi>) and the Lord <hi>Carew,</hi> to be Godfathers
<pb facs="tcp:57430:5"/>to the Children, being much Admirers of the novelty of the thing. Neither could the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſuppoſe, or intend his Book uſeful to forreign parts, it being publiſhed in an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Dialect (no Language be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more current than the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.) It will therefore conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently be concluded, that it was meant for the Engliſh, his Countrey-folk, whether at home, or in forreign Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and undertaken by the Author, becauſe, in all his Readings of Authors (and thoſe not a few) he had not ſeen any that had written in ſo plain and perſpicuous a method (as may appear by peruſing it,)
<pb facs="tcp:57430:6"/>and ſuitable ſchemes in various figures, ſufficient to direct and inform Midwives in their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: As alſo, to contribute all things neceſſary in ſuch caſes. The Author therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends this Book to the Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of the moſt Grave and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Matrons of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> the firſt being the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Nativity, the latter his Countrey, whil'ſt obliged to it. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>James Wolveridge.</signed>
               <dateline>From my Study in <hi>Cork,</hi> 
                  <date>Jan. 12 th. 1669/70.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" subtype="to_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:6"/>
            <head>To his deſerving Friend, <hi>Dr. James Wolveridge,</hi> On his <hi>Speculum Matricis.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF that <hi>Sicilian</hi> was admir'd, becauſe He fram'd the <hi>Machin</hi> which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd the Laws</l>
               <l>And motions of the greater World, what fame</l>
               <l>Shall equal be to eternize thy Name:</l>
               <l>Who greater ſecrets in ſo little can</l>
               <l>Unravel, in this leſſer world of man?</l>
               <l>Volumes that ſwell, like ore of Gold, have much</l>
               <l>Of earth and droſs, which ne're can paſs the touch;</l>
               <l>But in this little ſcheme, behold and ſee</l>
               <l>The eſſence and extract of Midwivery.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tredeskin</hi>'s nut-ſhell, or that Germane flye,</l>
               <l>Were ne'r compos'd with greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:7"/>
               <l>What pangs and throws do others brains torment,</l>
               <l>(Like <hi>Joves,</hi> which <hi>Pallas</hi> teem'd who ſcarce can vent</l>
               <l>What they contrive, who labour to enſure</l>
               <l>That which Abortive proves, and not mature.</l>
               <l>But thou hadſt quick delivery, thy brain</l>
               <l>Ne're wanted Midwife, neither felt it pain:</l>
               <l>In this thy true Production, which from thee</l>
               <l>Came like full-ripe fruit dropping from the tree:</l>
               <l>The Ladies, ſure, their glaſſes will neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,</l>
               <l>When on thy mirrour they ſhall once reflect,</l>
               <l>Which teaches to preſerve their beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties more</l>
               <l>Than all their Paints and Waſhes e're before.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Ionathan Aſhe, è Coll. Oriell, Oxon.</hi> A.M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" subtype="to_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:7"/>
            <head>Author in Libellum, ejuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>;picta Schemata.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>QUaeritur ovata quare ſit ſculpta fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura,</l>
               <l>Demonstrans faetum pagina quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuum?</l>
               <l>Omnia credibile eſt formari Animalia ab Ovo,</l>
               <l>Poſſe ſui generis tale referre genus.</l>
               <l>Cernis ut ova trahit ſolers formica, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore</l>
               <l>Parvula, quae in cumulos Irrequieta locat.</l>
               <l>Ovorum ex numero ſunt ſubventanea, (Inertis Molae instar) pullos non paritura ſuos:</l>
               <l>Hinc hominum, pecudum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> genus, genus omne ferarum</l>
               <l>Fit sterile, &amp; sterilis dedecus arbor habet;</l>
               <l>Edere ſed foecunda mihi ſperare licebit,</l>
               <l>Ova<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Prolifica ponere fida manu.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:8"/>
               <l>Sin ſecus, Obstetricum nullos Quaeſita Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bores</l>
               <l>Gens hominum, ceſſet, vel labefacta Ruat.</l>
               <l>Sic parere, aut calamus doceat parere, precamur:</l>
               <l>Illud naturae eſt, hoc erit Artis opus.</l>
               <l>Anſer Ovans alas ſcriptoribus explicat, artes</l>
               <l>Inde docens, variis picta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>; ſchematibus.</l>
               <l>Ille meam pennis, ſi ſit culpabilis, Artem</l>
               <l>Delirare ſuis, &amp; volitare dedit.</l>
               <l>Ova traham Reliquos ſcriptores inter, Acervo</l>
               <l>Pulchrum erit ex magno tollere delicias.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>James Wolveridge.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" subtype="to_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:8"/>
            <head>On the Praiſe, and the happy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of <hi>James Wolveridge, Dr.</hi> of Phyſick, in his labours on the Labour of Women, &amp;c.</head>
            <byline>Delivered by <hi>Aquila Smyth,</hi> M. D.</byline>
            <lg>
               <l>HEre is the Key unlocks a Cabinet,</l>
               <l>So quick, ſo ſafe, by art not known as yet:</l>
               <l>More friendly than the gourd o're <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> head,</l>
               <l>It breaks the <hi>Hymen,</hi> and the Maiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</l>
               <l>What ſhall I ſay! myſterious is thy art,</l>
               <l>But ſo, that labour labours in no ſmart;</l>
               <l>Thy clouded Genius 'mid'ſt the Curtain foggs,</l>
               <l>Swallows thy worth in the <hi>Hybernian</hi> boggs;</l>
               <l>Diſmantle then thy ſelf, appear to be</l>
               <l>Happy to all in thy delivery.</l>
               <l>So the production of thy brain ſhall make</l>
               <l>Midwives themſelves produce; and for thy ſake</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:9"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> teeming thus, man-Midwives out a birth,</l>
               <l>That is the product to the globe, and earth:</l>
               <l>But whilſt thy brain doth labour, we do too</l>
               <l>Bring but an Embrion out, which though t'out-do</l>
               <l>Mountains (full gravidated, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce</l>
               <l>A mouſe) when thou doſt open natures ſluce;</l>
               <l>So riper ſeeds are ſown on barren ground,</l>
               <l>So th'Reaper hath a ſickly harveſt found.</l>
               <l>The pregnant <hi>pia mater</hi> of thy brain</l>
               <l>Doth ſettle in his place the womb a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain:</l>
               <l>There is no <hi>Mola</hi> in thy wit, what's here,</l>
               <l>Of truth is the effect and character.</l>
               <l>Teeming this nine moneths, we did ſurely look</l>
               <l>That thou ſhould'ſt be delivered of thy Book;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:9"/>
               <l>Prodigious Birth! who e're the like did know</l>
               <l>A child brought forth, ſtraitt to a Midwife grow?</l>
               <l>Ceaſe nature now thy tyrannies in vain,</l>
               <l>Here's one doth teach to mitigate a pain,</l>
               <l>Sets open Natures Gate, ſo that the birth</l>
               <l>Walks from the mother-womb to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-earth:</l>
               <l>No throws we have in this, no skreaks, no cryes,</l>
               <l>No Inſtruments, no Cupping of the thighes:</l>
               <l>Here is an Art that after-age will boaſt,</l>
               <l>And tell how <hi>Wolv'ridge</hi> hath deliver'd moſt</l>
               <l>With eaſe, producing forth what's ſafe we ſee,</l>
               <l>To which whole Colledges thy Goſſips be.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Septemb.</hi> 9th. 1669.</date> Cork.</dateline>
               <signed>Your Devoted Friend and Servant, whilst <hi>Aquila Smyth, M. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" subtype="to_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:10"/>
            <head>Ad Authorem, Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miaſtichon.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ABdita dum teneri pandis myſteria foetus</l>
               <l>Numina ſecretis quae poſuere locis,</l>
               <l>Diverſis diverſa paras medicamina mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis;</l>
               <l>Picta refers variis ſchemata multa mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis;</l>
               <l>Signa<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conceptus monstras, ſignantia ſexum,</l>
               <l>Sive puella ſiet, ſit ve puella puer</l>
               <l>Obstetricas; varias calamo monstrante figuras,</l>
               <l>Qua methodo mulier ſit paritura doces.</l>
               <l>Nuribus, Infanti, Medicaris matribus aeque;</l>
               <l>Dum te nec lactis cura vel ulla latet.</l>
               <l>Nonjacet Aurato licet ulla puerpera lecto, manu.</l>
               <l>Ipſe struis facili mollia lecta manu:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:10"/>
               <l>Parturit ipſe liber, dum pro ſponſoribus aſtant</l>
               <l>Zoilus aut Momus, parturit imo ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid:</l>
               <l>Quem Matrona gravis ſi qua lactaverit ulnis,</l>
               <l>Et dederit Cunas, has vagus orbis agat.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dabam Cork. <date>17 Calendas Octobris, 1669.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Honoris &amp; Amoris ergo dicavit, Jonathan Aſhe è Coll. Oriel, Oxon. A.M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" subtype="to_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:11"/>
            <head>In Authorem, Amicum ſuum Integerrimum.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>PErlege (Lector;) opus, <hi>Wolv'rigii;</hi> quod tibi aperte</l>
               <l>Oſtendit docti pectora digna viri,</l>
               <l>Hoc; ſecreta ſuis naturae vultibus ornat,</l>
               <l>Ordine perſpicuo conſpicienda patent:</l>
               <l>Codice nam clari Doctoris dicta <hi>Jacobi:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Alter <hi>Galenus, Juſtinianus</hi> Item)</l>
               <l>Qui quorum merito; ſtudiis, ſatis acta duorum</l>
               <l>Voluerat, &amp; Tomos quoſlibet ille ſuis.</l>
               <l>Hic decus, hic lumen, hic fons ſermone Latino</l>
               <l>Orbis, en! Emeritus tempus in omne micans,</l>
               <l>Cujus florebit ſtudioſos inter utroſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Perpetuo Juris, non minus Artis Amor.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Danielis Colman. J. V. D.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex Muſaeolo meo in Subur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biis Borealibus Coreagiae,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Idibus Septembris, 1669.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_book">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:11"/>
            <head>The Author to his Book.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>GO little Book, I envy not thy hap,</l>
               <l>Mayſt thou be dandled in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies lap;</l>
               <l>I hope the Ladies will not thee diſdain,</l>
               <l>Th'art clean, though in a home-ſpun dreſs, and plain:</l>
               <l>Nor mayſt thou to a gaudy Garb aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</l>
               <l>Thy native Idiom is thy beſt attire;</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Phydias</hi> and <hi>Apelles</hi> do declare,</l>
               <l>Such Schemes of Births in thee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted rare;</l>
               <l>Thou ſhew'ſt no monſtrous births that may affright,</l>
               <l>(Though thou might'ſt do't) but ſuch as may delight,</l>
               <l>With admiration; then go kiſs their hands,</l>
               <l>Tell them th'art ſubject unto their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:12"/>
               <l>Thy Countrey dreſs compoſed for their good,</l>
               <l>Brooks no ſcurrilities, if underſtood</l>
               <l>By Graveſt Matrons, never penn'd, nor meant</l>
               <l>To be the ſubject of a looſe intent;</l>
               <l>Nor yet to pleaſe laſcivious, wanton eyes,</l>
               <l>Whoſe thoughts to <hi>Venus</hi> are a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</l>
               <l>Go viſit Nunneries, whoſe chaſter fate</l>
               <l>Perchance may pregnant be without a mate;</l>
               <l>Except bald time, with his ſuſpected pate</l>
               <l>Teach th'Abbeſs Midwivery within her grate;</l>
               <l>Be there <hi>probat</hi>'neer but a year, and then,</l>
               <l>If uſeleſs, hope thou mayſt come out again.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perlustrate</hi> all the World, let women know</l>
               <l>To help themſelves, their children, nurſes too.</l>
               <l>Viſit the Nurſeries of Learnings fame,</l>
               <l>Salute thoſe fountains in thy Authors name;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:12"/>
               <l>Their pardon crave, whilſt not from diſreſpect</l>
               <l>They are accoſted in a dialect</l>
               <l>As uncouth to his pen as to their view,</l>
               <l>which had been dreſt up in another hiew,</l>
               <l>Had he been ſure to have been under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood,</l>
               <l>(As was his only ſcope) for publick good;</l>
               <l>Yet mayſt thou be ſo whereſoe're th'art brought,</l>
               <l>May't not be ſaid that thou art good for nought:</l>
               <l>Beware the Preſs a-while, 'twere better tarry,</l>
               <l>Leſt being preſt too hard thou mayſt miſcarry.</l>
               <l>If't muſt be ſo, thoſe Med'cines of thy own</l>
               <l>Muſt cure thy ſad Abortion, or elſe none:</l>
               <l>Nor art thou ſmutty to ſet out thy fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</l>
               <l>But yet mayſt ſhew the curious works of nature.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:13"/>
               <l>Teach Ladies Nett-work then, and tell them plain</l>
               <l>They have a wondrous nett-work 'bout their brain;</l>
               <l>And yet thy fringed skirt adorn'd may be</l>
               <l>With ornaments, and by Authority.</l>
               <l>Here's Veſt and Tunick, <hi>Amnios,</hi> and <hi>Chorion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Jus de corae</hi> too, that thou be in faſhion:</l>
               <l>We admit no <hi>Allantoides</hi> in the leaſt,</l>
               <l>Becauſe thou treat'ſt of man, and not of beaſt.</l>
               <l>Th'art furniſh'd with a Royal Saſh (withall,</l>
               <l>Ne'r out of faſhion) Cord, Umbilical;</l>
               <l>When all is done, then let thy ſchemes and faſhions</l>
               <l>Succesful prove to future Generations.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem__acrostic_to_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:13"/>
            <head>To my moſt Worthy Friend, Dr. <hi>James Wolveridge,</hi> upon his Book, <hi>Speculum Matricis.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head>AN ACHROSTICK.</head>
               <l>If I were skill'd in <hi>Chaldaick,</hi> or in <hi>Syriack,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As others, who might well thy Praiſes ſhew;</l>
               <l>My muſe would then compell a Panegyrick</l>
               <l>Even for the debt which to thy worth I owe;</l>
               <l>S ith I to that could never yet attain,</l>
               <l>Which makes thee famous in the Art of Phyſick,</l>
               <l>Or imitate thy Great Heroick strain,</l>
               <l>Lo, I begin to try in tones of Lyrick.</l>
               <l>Let Grave Phyſitians greet thee with a kiſs,</l>
               <l>Vnskilful Quacks may hence learn to amend,</l>
               <l>Expell their poyſons, which for want of this</l>
               <l>Rent many a heart, and brought untimely end:</l>
               <l>I mean, becauſe they knew not mans first being,</l>
               <l>Do ſtill mistake; I ſay't cannot be fit</l>
               <l>Giving Remedies which in no way are 'greeing</l>
               <l>Expreſs mens ruine by preſcribing it.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Obliged Friend, Richard Sampſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:14"/>
            <head>An INDEX con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Contents Alphabetically.</head>
            <list type="index">
               <item>A.
<list>
                     <item>ABortion
<list>
                           <item>what, with its cauſes and ſings. Page 104, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>How prevented, and cured, pag. 112, &amp;c.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Air ambient dangerous in child-bed p. 111.116.</item>
                     <item>After-pains what, their cauſes, and cure p. 133, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>After-burden
<list>
                           <item>what it is. p. 84, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>Why ſo called. p. 90, 91, 92, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>Muſt be brought away, and why. Its danger being left behind. How it is hindred in its coming forth. How drawn out. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:15"/>
                     <item>Aged women
<list>
                           <item>commonly bring forth females, and why. p. 101.</item>
                           <item>They are ſubject to the falling down of the womb p. 163</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Age of the beſt nurſe deſcribed p. 141</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Allantois</hi> part of the ſecundine (in beaſts, but not to be found in men) and is as a girdle p. 90</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Amnios</hi> the inward membrane of the ſecundine p. 89, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Anger in nurſes naught p. 143</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aorta</hi> what arterie, and how genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted p. 8</item>
                     <item>Arterial vein what it is <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Aſtringent powder uſeful for Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives p. 30</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>B.
<list>
                     <item>BAgg deſcribed. Page 76. &amp;c. In uſe.</item>
                     <item>Behaviour of nurſes to be enquired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to p. 124, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Birth natural what, and how, deſcribed p. 24. How facilitated 110.130</item>
                     <item>Blood after conception diſtinguiſhed three waies p. 14.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:15"/>
                     <item>Bones generated from the ſeed p. 12.</item>
                     <item>Botches in children, their cauſes p. 115.145</item>
                     <item>Brains, how generated, and for what p. 9, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Breath ſtinking argues a child dead, and putrified in the womb p. 79</item>
                     <item>Breaſts ſore to cure p. 101</item>
                     <item>Breeding women, what forbidden them p. 101</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>C.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CApſula</hi> of the heart generated p. 6</item>
                     <item>Cake of the womb what p. 88, 89, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Cartilages whence generated p. 11</item>
                     <item>Cataplaſms
<list>
                           <item>againſt a looſneſs in child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. 137.</item>
                           <item>Againſt miſcarrying, to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the navil p. 118</item>
                           <item>Cataplaſme in caſe of ſore breaſts p. 102</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Caudles in after-pains, and in caſe any of the ſecundine be left behind p. 134</item>
                     <item>Cauſes of immoderate flowing of the <hi>Lochia</hi> in child-bed, with their cure p. 119, 120.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:16"/>
                     <item>Cautions to Midwives in their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs p. 28, 29</item>
                     <item>a Caution to the Iriſh women in a looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs p. 105</item>
                     <item>Child, when ſo properly called p. 112</item>
                     <item>Child-bearing women ought to be cheerful p. 110</item>
                     <item>Children
<list>
                           <item>how overlaid, with the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. p. 141.</item>
                           <item>Of their pining away 150</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Chorion what, and why ſo called p. 88</item>
                     <item>Coats of the Arteries, whence p. 11</item>
                     <item>Cold in child-bed dangerous, with its cure p. 124</item>
                     <item>Cold dangerous in Child-bearing 111</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Calostrat,</hi> what children p. 144</item>
                     <item>Conception, with its ſigns 95, 96, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Conception in Nurſes make the child diſeaſed p. 144</item>
                     <item>Conditions of Nurſes to be inquired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, with her complexion p. 143</item>
                     <item>Convulſion-fits in infants, whence, and how cured 134, 135</item>
                     <item>Cordials
<list>
                           <item>againſt fainting fits, p 112.</item>
                           <item>A general excellent Cordial-water, p. 113.</item>
                           <item>Againſt a nauſeous ſtomack p. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:16"/>
                     <item>Coſtiveneſs the cauſe of difficult birth p. 35</item>
                     <item>Coſtivenes in breeding women naught, how it may be prevented p. 112</item>
                     <item>Cotyledons of the womb what p. 104</item>
                     <item>Courſes, why ſtop'd after conception, p. 14. How they are to be provoked p. 115, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>They are ſtirred up by the uſe of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery, &amp; are deſtructive to milk p. 144</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cranium</hi> what, &amp; how generated p. 10</item>
                     <item>Critical Fevers in child-bed, their cure p. 123, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Crying in children diſcovers want of milk p. 151</item>
                     <item>Cupping-glaſſes how, and where to be applyed p. 147</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>D.
<list>
                     <item>DAncing in the child-bearing wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or running, naught for the child p. 110</item>
                     <item>Dancing of the child a good exerciſe for the Nurſe p. 147</item>
                     <item>Danger from being not well purged in child-bed p. 115, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>a Decoction againſt too much milk p. 148</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:17"/>
                     <item>Dead child,
<list>
                           <item>how delivered of p. 93, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>ſigns of a dead child p. 102, &amp;c. 108.131.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Diet
<list>
                           <item>preſcribed for breeding women p. 111.</item>
                           <item>For child-bed women p. 120</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Diarrhaea,</hi> ſee Looſneſs in p. 131.136</item>
                     <item>Different poſtures of infants in the womb, why p. 78</item>
                     <item>Difficult births, their cauſes p. 34, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Diſtinction of parts, when p. 12</item>
                     <item>Dreams in the infant diſcover want of milk p. 151</item>
                     <item>Dropſies, how diſtinguiſhed from a <hi>Mola,</hi> or falſe conception p. 82</item>
                     <item>Drunkenneſs not to be indured in nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, p. 140</item>
                     <item>The <hi>dura mater,</hi> how generated p. 10</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>E.
<list>
                     <item>EAting fleſh in child-bed the cauſe of Fevers p. 124</item>
                     <item>Eating and drinking to be obſerved by nurſes p. 143</item>
                     <item>Eight moneths birth
<list>
                           <item>not like to live. p. 19, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>The reaſons <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Emplaſter
<list>
                           <item>againſt abortion p. 113.132</item>
                           <item>Againſt Convulſions in infants p.
<pb facs="tcp:57430:17"/> 135, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>Againſt the inconveniency of milk to be applyed in the breaſts p. 122.146</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Embryon what p. 87</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Epar uterinum,</hi> that is, the liver of the womb, what, its uſe, and why ſo called p. 86, 88</item>
                     <item>Exerciſe
<list>
                           <item>attenuates milk. p. 146.</item>
                           <item>In the nurſe good for the child p. 147</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Experiments to know if a woman hath conceived or no p. 98, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Experiments to try milk p. 126</item>
                     <item>The Excrements are not voided by the fundament whilſt the child is in the womb p. 16, &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>F.
<list>
                     <item>FAlſe conception
<list>
                           <item>what. p. 79.</item>
                           <item>How it differs from a true conception p. 81.</item>
                           <item>How diſtinguiſhed from a Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. p. 82.</item>
                           <item>How delivered of p. 94</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Falling out of the womb p. 162, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Fainting fits in breeding women, how prevented p. 112</item>
                     <item>Fevers in child-bed in general, and of a Fever of milk, what it is, with the cures p. 121</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:18"/>
                     <item>Female when conceived, and how known p. 200</item>
                     <item>Fibres in the firſt generation what p. 2</item>
                     <item>Figure of a child of 18 daies old p. 12</item>
                     <item>Fume, or ſuffumigation in fits of the mother p. 160</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>G.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>GAlea</hi> is part of that coat of the ſecundine called the <hi>Amnios</hi> p. 87</item>
                     <item>a General cordial water againſt all fainting fits, at all times p. 128</item>
                     <item>a Gibbous infant the cauſe of a difficult birth p. 35</item>
                     <item>Glyſters
<list>
                           <item>for a looſeneſs in child-bed. p. 136, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>For the retention of the <hi>Lochia</hi> then p. 116</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Gluttony in nurſes condemned p. 143</item>
                     <item>Great breaſts, and great nipples in nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes not commendable, why p. 141</item>
                     <item>Grief
<list>
                           <item>in nurſes naught for the child. p. 143</item>
                           <item>Naught for child-bearing wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men p. 110</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Gripes in the belly of infants, whence p. 149</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:18"/>
               <item>H.
<list>
                     <item>HAndſome children, why ſome ſo, &amp; why others unhandſome p. 21</item>
                     <item>Haſtineſs in the Midwife not good p. 27, 29</item>
                     <item>Haſty riſing up of the mother naught for the child in the womb p. 110</item>
                     <item>Hard breaſts the ſigns of the infants thriving in the womb p. 101</item>
                     <item>Haemorrhoids the cauſe of difficult birth p. 35</item>
                     <item>Heart generated, when p. 6</item>
                     <item>Heat of the ſeed the cauſe of genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of males, they are generated in the right ſide p. 21</item>
                     <item>Helmet called the <hi>Galea,</hi> part of the <hi>Amnios</hi> p. 87</item>
                     <item>Heavy burdens carried by the mother are naught for the infant in the womb p. 111</item>
                     <item>Hyſterick fits: ſee Strangulation of the womb, and mother-fits p. 155, &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>I.
<list>
                     <item>INnate heat in infants requires con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant aliment p. 150</item>
                     <item>Infant,
<list>
                           <item>when ſaid to be, p. 16</item>
                           <item>How it
<pb facs="tcp:57430:19"/> lyeth in the womb, p. 33, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>How nouriſhed in the womb, p. 14</item>
                           <item>It at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts the pureſt blood, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Hath more from the mother then from the father, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Why like their Parents, p. 21</item>
                           <item>To know whether it thrive in the womb, or not p. 101</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Infants
<list>
                           <item>participate of the nurſes food, and phyſick, p. 151</item>
                           <item>How to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Midwife p. 29</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Impurities are communicated to them by the Qualities of the milk p. 151</item>
                     <item>Inflations the cauſe of after-pains p. 133</item>
                     <item>Inflammations of the womb the cauſe of difficult birth p. 35</item>
                     <item>Intemperance in nurſes the ruine of their nurſeries p. 140</item>
                     <item>Immoderate flowing of the <hi>Lochia</hi> in child-bed dangerous p. 118, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Juleps in caſe of retention of the <hi>Lochia</hi> in child-bed p. 118, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Againſt Convulſion-ſits in infants p. 135</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>K.
<list>
                     <item>KNots, as many as are to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the navil-ſtring, ſo many males p. 103</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>L.
<list>
                     <item>LAdies may nurſe their own chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with the greateſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies p. 135</item>
                     <item>Leprous infants, how ſo begoten p. 102</item>
                     <item>Liver
<list>
                           <item>firſt generated after the coats by the <hi>Vena bifurca,</hi> p. 4, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>Is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete blood <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lochia</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>retained in child-birth, dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, p. 115</item>
                           <item>Flowing over-much, dangerous alſo p. 119</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Looſnes in child-bed dangerous, p. 131.135</item>
                     <item>Lungs, when, and how generated p. 8</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>M.
<list>
                     <item>MAle conceived, how known p. 99</item>
                     <item>Man, his dignity, and titles, <hi>vid. Pref.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Manner of generation p. 2, 3</item>
                     <item>Marrow of the bones what, with its uſe p. 11</item>
                     <item>Matrix to be anointed in difficult births p. 40</item>
                     <item>Meats to be avoided by nurſes, what p. 144</item>
                     <item>Medicines uſual in Fevers of child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth p. 124</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:20"/>
                     <item>Members diſtinguiſhed by the tenth day p. 7</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Menstrua</hi> the cauſe of ſtrangulation of the womb, or fits of the mother p. 156</item>
                     <item>Midriff how made, p. 7.</item>
                     <item>The beſt Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife
<list>
                           <item>deſcribed, p. 27</item>
                           <item>Her poſture, p. 28, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>Her office, Number of her aſſiſtants, Her furniture <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Midwives are not to take more care of the infant then of the mother p. 93, 94</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Milk,
<list>
                           <item>how generated, p. 14.98</item>
                           <item>It is the cauſe of Fevers, p. 121</item>
                           <item>Driven back too ſoon dangerus, with the reaſons of it, p. 122</item>
                           <item>fried by its colour and quality, p. 145</item>
                           <item>Of milk too thick corrected, p. 146, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>Too thin cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How to cure the too great abundance, p. 147.</item>
                           <item>The want of milk ſupplyed, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>No milk at all, the worſt p. 150</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mirth
<list>
                           <item>good in breeding women, p. 110</item>
                           <item>In the nurſe, beſt for the child p. 141</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mola,</hi> or falſe conception, what p. 79</item>
                     <item>Mother contributes more to the infant
<pb facs="tcp:57430:20"/> then doth the father p. 15</item>
                     <item>Motion too violent in the nurſe, naught for the child, and ſo in the mother p. 147</item>
                     <item>Mourning
<list>
                           <item>either in the mother, naught for the infant in the womb, p. 43</item>
                           <item>Or for the nurſe <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mothers, if able, fitteſt to nurſe their own p. 152</item>
                     <item>Mother-fits,
<list>
                           <item>ſee ſtrangulation of the womb, p. 155.</item>
                           <item>How cured, p. 159</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mucilage what p. 126</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>N.
<list>
                     <item>NAtural form of birth, what it is p. 24</item>
                     <item>Nauſeouſneſs prevented p. 113</item>
                     <item>Navil
<list>
                           <item>how generated p. 3.</item>
                           <item>How to be cut, <hi>ib.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How it atracts blood for nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, p. <hi>ib.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Cords of the navil, ſo many twins 103</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Needing what p. 108</item>
                     <item>Nerves
<list>
                           <item>of the back, their original, p. 11</item>
                           <item>How diſperſed through the whole body by a figure p. 13</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Nipples,
<list>
                           <item>what are the beſt, p. 141, &amp;c.</item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:57430:21"/>
                           <item>Sore nipples to cure p. 137, &amp;c.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Nurſes
<list>
                           <item>the beſt, deſcribed, p. 140, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>Not to be choſen in poverty, p. 150.</item>
                           <item>Nurſes purged to cure the child, why p. 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>Nurſes not to rock the infant too vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently preſently after ſuckling it, why p. 153</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>O.
<list>
                     <item>ORiginal
<list>
                           <item>of the nerves, p. 10</item>
                           <item>Of the ſpine of the back <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Oxycrat what p. 129</item>
                     <item>Oyles,
<list>
                           <item>what fit for Midwives, p. 26</item>
                           <item>Their uſe in difficult births p. 41</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ointment
<list>
                           <item>in caſe of the <hi>Lochia</hi> ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, p. 118</item>
                           <item>in caſe of too immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate flux of them, p. 120</item>
                           <item>An excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ointment in a difficult birth, p. 41.126</item>
                           <item>For ſore nipples, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>In Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterick fits p. 160</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>P.
<list>
                     <item>PArſly an enemie to milk p. 144</item>
                     <item>Paſſions in the nurſe hinder good milk p. 143</item>
                     <item>Pains in child-bearing, whence they are p. 23.133</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:21"/>
                     <item>Pains after the child-birth, what p. 52.116.124</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pericardium</hi> generated with the heart Piles in hyſterick fits p. 161</item>
                     <item>Planets, their aſpect, the cauſe of good features and forms in children, and of bad p. 21</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Placenta uteri</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>what, p. 86, 88.</item>
                           <item>But one, though there be never ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants; Its uſe <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Plenty of milk ever beſt, p. 142</item>
                     <item>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of the infant
<list>
                           <item>many, p. 37, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>Poſtures of the infant naturally, how, p. 33</item>
                           <item>Many praeternatural poſtures deſcribed in ſixteen ſeveral figures, from p. 37, to p. 72</item>
                           <item>Their helps re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by way of Dialogue <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Potions uſeful in difficult births p. 134</item>
                     <item>Powders
<list>
                           <item>for ſneezing in difficult births, p. 127, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>Againſt Abortion, p. 131</item>
                           <item>Againſt Convulſion-fits in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, p. 136</item>
                           <item>Againſt immoderate flowings of the <hi>Lochia</hi> in child-bed, p. 119</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Pulſatile veins from the great Artery of the heart p. 7</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:22"/>
                     <item>Purgation of women
<list>
                           <item>how long, p. 115</item>
                           <item>Not being well purged, dangerous <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Purge not to be given till ſeven daies after the birth, in caſe the <hi>Lochia</hi> be ſtop'd p. 117</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Puſtules and whelks in infants, their cauſe p. 149</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Q.
<list>
                     <item>QUalities of milk paſs into thoſe that are ſuckled by that milk p. 152</item>
                     <item>Quarrelſomeneſs in nurſes naught p. 143</item>
                     <item>Quicken, when women do p. 17</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>R.
<list>
                     <item>REmedies over-hot in difficult births, how inconvenient, p. 126, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Retention of the <hi>Lochia</hi> in child-bed dangerous, with its cauſes, and cure p. 116</item>
                     <item>Riding in the mother naught for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant p. 110</item>
                     <item>Rocking of the infant too vehemently preſently after ſucking naught p. 153</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:22"/>
                     <item>Running in the mother naught for the infant p. 110</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>S.
<list>
                     <item>SColding in nurſes not tollerable p. 142</item>
                     <item>a Scruple what p. 128</item>
                     <item>Scull, how generated p. 10</item>
                     <item>Seventh moneth birth may live p. 19</item>
                     <item>Secundine
<list>
                           <item>what, p. 84</item>
                           <item>Deſcribed by figures p. 85</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sexes diſtinguiſhed p. 99</item>
                     <item>Sixth moneth birth cannot live p. 19</item>
                     <item>Signs mortal by the infants motion in the womb p. 20</item>
                     <item>Sleep
<list>
                           <item>in the mother good for the infant, p. 11</item>
                           <item>Often ſleep in nurſes is good for the infant p. 141</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sluttiſh nurſes make naſty children p. 140</item>
                     <item>Sneezing
<list>
                           <item>good in difficult births, p. 127, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>And in fits of the mother p. 159</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Soul when infuſed p. 17</item>
                     <item>Spine of the back,
<list>
                           <item>how generated, p. 11</item>
                           <item>What it is, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Its uſe <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Stature of the nurſe p. 104</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:23"/>
                     <item>Stinking things and ſmells, how uſeful in mother-fits p. 161</item>
                     <item>Stool for Midwives deſcribed p. 28</item>
                     <item>Stone in the bladder the cauſe of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult birth p. 35</item>
                     <item>Stopping of the terms no ſure ſign of conception p. 95</item>
                     <item>Strangulation of the womb
<list>
                           <item>a fierce di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, p. 155</item>
                           <item>Its definition. What it is, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Parts affected what, the cauſes, p. 156</item>
                           <item>Signs of the fit in its augmentation, ſtate, and declination, p. 157</item>
                           <item>How it differs from a Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope, or Swouning, 158, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>How from an Apoplexy, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from an Epilepſie, p. 159</item>
                           <item>Its cure <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Strength, how to be reſtored p. 123</item>
                     <item>a Suffumigation
<list>
                           <item>in fears of Abortion, p. 113</item>
                           <item>In hyſterick fits 160</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Superfoetation what 102</item>
                     <item>Suppoſitories,p. 124
<list>
                           <item>For infants, p. 136</item>
                           <item>In the ſtrangulation of the womb p. 255</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sweet ſmells, how uſed in fits of the mother p. 161</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:23"/>
                     <item>Symptoms grievous in breeding women,
<list>
                           <item>their danger, how corrected, p. 24</item>
                           <item>In child-bed women not well purged, dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous p. 112</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>T.
<list>
                     <item>TArtneſs of milk, how corrected p. 146</item>
                     <item>Terms in child-bearing to help p. 113</item>
                     <item>Timpany, how cauſed p. 82</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Truncus phrenicus</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>what, p. 7</item>
                           <item>The trunk of the hollow vein, aſcending and deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing p. 5</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Tryal of milk p. 135</item>
                     <item>Twins have ſo many navil-cords as there are twins, and yet but one <hi>Placenta</hi> p. 103</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>V.
<list>
                     <item>VEin
<list>
                           <item>hollow what, p. 9</item>
                           <item>Vein two forked what; Its oſe, p. 3</item>
                           <item>The Venal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, with its uſe p. 7</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Venery, and its uſe, ſpoyl the milk in the nurſe p. 144</item>
                     <item>Venereous thoughts in the nurſe ſpoyl the milk <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ugly children, the reaſon why they are ſo p. 21</item>
                     <item>Vitious ſeed the cauſe of ſtrangulation of the womb p. 156</item>
                     <item>Virtue of the milk of a male child, if a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male ſuck it; and of a female, if a male ſuck it p. 145</item>
                     <item>Unguent againſt Abortion, p. 41.126. See Ointment.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:24"/>
                     <item>Vomit of Oxymell good to attenuate thick milk p. 146</item>
                     <item>Urine of the infant in the womb, by what paſſages voided in the womb p. 16</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>W.
<list>
                     <item>WAnt of milk, the cauſes, and cure p. 147</item>
                     <item>Wateriſh humors flowing out of the breaſts of its own accord, is an argument of a weak child p. 105</item>
                     <item>Weakneſs of the matrix is the cauſe of the ſecundine not coming forth p. 90</item>
                     <item>Whelps dye with ſucking women p. 142</item>
                     <item>Winds ſharp and cold not good for the child in the womb p. 106</item>
                     <item>Women
<list>
                           <item>meet helps for man, p. 27</item>
                           <item>Fit helps for women, by reaſon of the modeſty of their Sex, p. 27, &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>How delivered, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>How long to keep their beds in child-bed with ſafety p. 115</item>
                           <item>Women above 40 years old bring forth with more difficulty, p. 30
<list>
                                 <item>They are to be dealt withal in child-bed, as with wounded per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons p. 124</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Womb,
<list>
                           <item>its natural property to receive ſeed, p. 1</item>
                           <item>The falling out of it, p. 162</item>
                           <item>The ſigns, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The cauſes, p. 163.</item>
                           <item>Prognoſticks, and cure p. 164</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Y.
<list>
                     <item>A YEar ſufficient for a child to be ſuckled p. 153</item>
                     <item>Young women bring forth males moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, why p. 100, &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>The end of the Table.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:24"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince all Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences tend to the uſe and benefit of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, all things by the Almighty Creator being ſubjected to him, who is no other than a little World in himſelf: Man would not only be ungrateful to his Creator, but wanting to his off-ſpring, ſhould he not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to improve his whole indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Reaſon, and skill, to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<pb facs="tcp:57430:25"/>his kind to all poſterity. And therefore, beſides other helps, as Phyſical, Anatomical, and Diaete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, &amp;c. The art and skill of Obstetricie (commonly called Midwivery) is none of the leaſt:<note place="margin">Non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor est virtus quam quaerere parta tueri.</note> It being no leſs virtue and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to preſerve a child when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, than content and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in begetting; in both which, both Sexes are, and ought equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be concerned; for where the womb proves the tomb, there is neither room for Phyſick, Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, Chirurgery, or diet, &amp;c. or any thing like it. This then being the firſt work in reference to mans future well-doing, laying aſide all other Argumentative circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locutions, and deviations; let us,
<pb facs="tcp:57430:25"/>by way of diſcourſe, examine, and contrive, how that creature man may be preſerved, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Conception, to the hour of his birth, and that with ſafety too to her that bare him. And truly, it may be worth the while, if we conſider the excellency of man, whom ſome call (as like unto God,<note place="margin">The dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſo) The Interpreter of the gods. <hi>Pythagoras</hi> calls him The Meaſure of all things; And <hi>Plato</hi> calls him The Wonder of Wonders. <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> stiles him The Great Pattern of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> terms him A Politick Animal, born for ſociety, whom God made with his face upright; whereas all other creatures look with their faces downward.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Prona<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Ovid. Met am. Lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cum ſpectant ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malia caetera terram; Os homini ſublime dedit, coelum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tueri Juſſit, &amp; erectos ad ſydera tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere vultus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontem corporeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reorum. Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis &amp; conſilii. Mundi Epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; naturae delicias. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>P. 8. ve. 4, 5,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Syneſius</hi> terms man the Horizon of all corporeal and incorporeals. <hi>Tully</hi> calls him a Divine creature, full of Reaſon &amp; counſel; whom <hi>Pliny</hi> alſo calls the Epitomy of the World, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of Nature: And whom all with one conſent, call, a <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme,</hi> a little world in a bigger. Of whom, the Kingly Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> in Pſalme the <hi>8th.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou haſt made him little lower than the Angels; thou haſt crowned him with glory and honour, and haſt placed him over all the works of thy hands.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:26"/>Now then, man being ſo excellent a Creature, who, though the laſt in the Creation, yet not the leaſt; God making him as after his own Image and Likeneſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> the 1 Chap. ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 26, 27.</note> and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting him with ſo large a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, (and a bleſſing annexed to it) as to ſubdue the Creation, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all the creatures ſubject to the dominion of man, whom God had or dained as his Vice-Roy on earth, with this bleſſing, <hi>viz.</hi> be fruitful, and multiply, and reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the earth: Let us make a nearer indagation and ſcrutiny into the formation of man, as to the order of the generation of the parts, and increaſe of the infant, according to the daies and times, from the firſt conception till the
<pb facs="tcp:57430:27"/>day of his birth: And then, the more we ſeriouſly weigh it, and pry into it,<note place="margin">Pſ. 139. ver. 13.</note> the more, with the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, we ſhall admire our Creator by our creation, and bleſs that God that hath cover'd us in our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers womb, and praiſing him, ſay; <hi>We are fearfully &amp; wonderfully made, marvellous are thy works,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 15. <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. My bones <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Verſ. 16.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. My fubſtance was not hid from thee when I was made in ſecret; and curiouſly wrought in the loweſt parts of the Earth. Thine eyes did ſee my ſubſtance yet being unper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and in thy Book all my members were written, which in continuance were faſhioned, when as yet there was none of them.</hi> And if God, who created
<pb facs="tcp:57430:27"/>male and female, thought it fit to provide the woman as a help meet for him:<note place="margin">Gen. 2.20.</note> Women being moſt fit to help women in their deliveries, by reaſon of the modeſty of their ſex; It ſhall be the whole ſubject of this enſuing ſmall Tract, to deſcribe a Midwife, and ſuch a woman too that may be moſt apt for ſo neceſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry an employment; and then (ſtill aiming at a publick good) decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that <hi>Idiom</hi> beſt becoming the Pen of Doctors,<note place="margin">The Latin Tongue.</note> ſhall ſhape my Quill to an Engliſh Dialect, and (avoiding intricate and Bomba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick words, and Acroamatical ſentences, where they may be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe expreſſed) afford ſuch mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial directory aſſiſtance in the buſineſs of Midwivery, as ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:57430:28"/>be ſuitable to the meaneſt capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; not preſuming to inſtruct the Learned,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Noctuas Athenas.</note> leſt I ſeem to bring Owls to <hi>Athens;</hi> but to inform the leſs knowing. And ending this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, we will begin with Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelf, and the reſt in Order.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57430:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Of the True generation of the Parts, and Increaſe of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant in the Womb, according to the daies and times, till the time of the Birth.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the womb.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the womb (whoſe property it is naturally to receive ſeed unto genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as a Loadſtone at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts iron, or as Jeat ſtraws or feathers) hath received the ſeed for generation, and by its virtue hath ſhut up the ſeed for generation; Preſently, from the firſt day untill the ſixth or ſeventh, there grow and ariſe very many and very ſmall fibres or hairs, beginning with a hot motion,<note place="margin">See the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</note> by which vital heat the liver with his chiefeſt organs are generated by a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57430:29"/>virtue; as this following Scheme may the more illuſtrate, marked as in the margin.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>The ſmall firſt fibres.</p>
               <figDesc>depiction of an embryo</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>For the vital ſpirits, giving down ſeed towards conception, forms and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth the chiefeſt members by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57430:29"/>the tenth day, being let in by certain veins of the ſecundine,<note place="margin">The navil' how gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated.</note> to which the matrix is fixed, and by which the blood is imported, and of which the navil is generated.</p>
            <p>But at the very ſame time three ſmal ſpots (not unlike to curds of milk) ariſe, where the liver, the heart,<note place="margin">Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Infant by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. <hi>Vena bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furca.</hi>
               </note> and the brain have their places; and then preſently a vein directed by the navil, attracts the thicker blood confuſed with the ſeed, and makes it fit for nouriſhment: from whence alſo there ariſeth a vein with two forks, which is generated according to the form of this figure.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:57430:30"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the development of the navel in an embryo</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>In the one of which branches there is a collection of blood, of which firſt the liver is generated by a natural facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.<note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Liver.</note> From whence it eaſily appears, the liver to be a congealed and concrete blood: and alſo it may be manifeſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57430:30"/>how many and various veins it hath prepared and fitted, for the expulſive and attractive virtue. But in the other branch are generated thoſe textures, or rather web of veins, with the dilatation of other veins, as of the ſtomack, ſpleen, and inteſtines, in the lower part of the belly. And from hence immediately all veins are recollected together, as ſo many branches into one trunk, in the upper texture of the liver towards the hollow vein;<note place="margin">Venae Cavae truncus aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendens, deſcendens Diaphrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. truncus deſcendens.</note> and this trunk by and by ſends down branches to make the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff, and directs not a few branches to the lower parts, even to the very thighs: and then the heart, with his veins ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended into ſeed from the navil, is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated by a vital virtue,<note place="margin">Spina dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi.</note> and is directed towards the ſpine of the back, as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated in this figure, 3.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:57430:31"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the development of the liver and the branching of veins in an embryo</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>But thoſe do attract the hotteſt and more ſubtile blood,<note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the heart. <hi>Pericardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, vel Capſula Cordis.</hi>
               </note> of which the heart is generated, incaſed in a membrane, naturally fleſhy and thick, neceſſary up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of ſo hot a member. But the hollow vein extending it ſelf,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57430:31"/>and penetrating the inward concavity of the right ſide in the heart, &amp;c. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives thence blood for the nouriſhment of the heart. From the ſame branch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of this his vein, and in the ſame part another vein ariſeth, called, by ſome,<note place="margin">Truncus Phrenicus, vel Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> by ſome, the immoveable, or quiet vein; becauſe, according to the account of the pulſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of other veins it beats not at all, but lyes quiet; ordained for this end,<note place="margin">Vena Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronaria.</note> that it ſhould let go the pureſt blood to the lungs, being veſted with a double tunicle like an Arterie, from whence it is called the Arterial vein.<note place="margin">Vena ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terioſa, <hi>er</hi> Pulmona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</note> But in the left concavity of the heart there are two Arteries, that is to ſay, the Venal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, and the Great Arterie, which carries a great pulſe with it, and diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the vital ſpirits by the blood of the heart into all the pulſatile veins of the body. For, as the hollow vein is the original of all veins, by which the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy doth attract its whole nouriſhment of blood; ſo,<note place="margin">Aorta. Venae p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiles Aorta.</note> from the <hi>Aorta</hi> (or great Arterie) all pulſatile veins are derived, diffuſing the vital ſpirits through the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57430:32"/>whole body. For the heart is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and original of vital heat, without which no creature or member can thrive.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Arteria Venoſa.</note>Under the aboveſaid Arterie in the left concavity of the heart, another vein ariſeth called the Venal Arterie: And, although that be really a pulſatile vein, and doth direct the vital ſpirits, yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manner of all pulſatile veins that have blood, It hath but one coat, and therefore made for that end, that it ſhould derive the cold air from the lungs to refreſh the heart, as alſo to attemper its over-much heat.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the lungs.</note>And, becauſe veins iſſue out from both the concavities of the heart, and are inſerted into the lungs, and of which the lungs are formed; for the vein that proceeds from the right concavity of the heart produceth the moſt ſubtile blood, which by ſmall fibres diſperſed here and there, is changed into the fleſhy ſubſtance of the lungs. But from the great vein of the heart (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Aorta</hi>) and from the great vein of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57430:32"/>(<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Vena Cava,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vena Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va,</hi> the great vein of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, whence the breſt, arms, and thighs proceed.</note> or hollow vein) the whole breſt is generated, and ſo ſucceſſively the Arms and Thighs.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the development of the heart and arterial veins in an embryo</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Within the time aforeſaid alſo is generated the higheſt and chiefeſt part of this noble ſtructure,<note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the brain:</note> the Brain; in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57430:33"/>the third Region of this maſs; for the whole maſs of ſeed being filled with the animal ſpirits, that contracts a great part of the genital moyſture, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes it in a certain concavity wherein the brain may be formed: but, as to the out-ſide,<note place="margin">The <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,</hi> or the <hi>Dura mater.</hi> The Scull.</note> it is inveloped with a certain covering, which being toaſted and dried with heat, is brought into a boney ſubſtance, and becomes a ſcull, as appears by this precedent figure.</p>
            <p>But the brain is ſo formed, that it may conceive, retain, and change the natures of all the vital ſpirits, from whence alſo proceed the beginnings of all Reaſon, and of the Senſes: For, as veins have their original from the liver,<note place="margin">The ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of the nerves.</note> and as arteries have their riſe from the heart; ſo alſo nerves being of a ſofter and milder natural exiſtence, ariſe from the brain, and are not hollow as the veins are, but ſolid; for they are the firſt and chiefeſt inſtruments of all the ſenſes, by which the motions of all the ſenſes, by which the motions of all the ſenſes, by reaſon of the vital ſpirit, are juſtly made.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57430:33"/>
            <p>After the nerves,<note place="margin">The origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of the pith of the back-bone, called the Silver cord, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> cap. 12. ver. 6.</note> from the brain alſo is formed the pith of the back-bone, not of an unlike nature from the brain, ſo that it ſcarce can be called marrow, becauſe it hath no likeneſs to marrow, either by ſight, or in ſubſtance; for the marrow is a kind of ſuperfluous ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ariſing from the blood of the members,<note place="margin">The mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, what, and how generated. The <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulla,</hi> what.</note> appointed to moiſten and make the bones of the body grow; but the brain and pith of the back have their original from the ſeed, not depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the nouriſhment and growth of the other members, but that by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they might make private parts of the body,<note place="margin">The brain and <hi>Spina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis medulla</hi> ordained for the uſe and motion of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> for the uſe and motion of the ſenſes, that from thence all the other nerves may take their riſe. For, from the pith of the back many nerves ariſe, from which the body hath ſenſe and motion, as may appear by the difference betwixt the vital and animal faculties, as hath been before hinted.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cartila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, bones, &amp;c. gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the ſeed.</note>Moreover, here it is to be obſerved, that from the ſeed it ſelf cartilages, bones, coats of the veins of the liver,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57430:34"/>and of the arteries of the heart, the brain with the nerves, and again the tunicles, and as well other pannicles or membranes as thoſe that wrap up the infant, are generated; but from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per blood of the infant is the fleſh it ſelf ingendred, and all thoſe parts that are of a fleſhy ſubſtance; as the heart, the liver, and lungs: And then at length all theſe grow together by the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous blood, attracted by the ſmall veins of the navil, which are obſerved to be directed with their orifices into the womb.<note place="margin">All parts diſtinct by 18 daies.</note> All which are diſtinctly made by the eighteenth day of the firſt moneth, from the very conception, at which time it may be called ſeed, but afterwards it becometh to be, and is called a child;<note place="margin">When cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a child.</note> which the Ancients have comprehended in theſe two ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sex in lacte dies, ter ſunt in ſanguine trini,</l>
               <l>Biſſeni carnem, ter ſeni membra figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:34"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:35"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depictions of an embryo in the womb and of the development of the nerves</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <hi>The leſſer figure denotes the Nerves derived fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Back and diſperſed through the whole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The explanation of the larger figure ſee in the following page.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Croſs ſculpſit'</hi>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57430:35"/>
            <p>Engliſhed thus,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Six daies in milk, thrice three the ſeed's in blood;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Twice ſix makes fleſh, thrice ſix makes members good.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>FF Sheweth a young one of 18 daies (though ſome hold it but 14 daies in which all the members may be diſcerned apart.)</item>
                  <item>GG The four Umbilical Veſſels meeting in one.</item>
                  <item>HH How the Umbilical Veſſels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thick by degrees, that that doubt amongſt ſome may be reſolved, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſpring from the womb, or no.</item>
                  <item>III Sheweth how the Umbilical veins and arteries are ſpread throughout the <hi>Chorion</hi> by infinite branches.</item>
                  <item>KKK Sheweth the membrane called <hi>Amnios,</hi> in which ſweat and urine are gathered together, in which the infant ſwimmeth, and ſits as ſafe as in a Bath.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57430:36"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Of the Nutriment of the child in the womb, and by what nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment it is preſerved, and when it groweth up to be an Infant.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Infant, how nouriſhed.</note>WHileſt the young one is in the womb, it is nouriſhed by blood attracted by the navil; by which it is, that women after they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived have their terms ſtop'd;<note place="margin">Why cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſtop'd after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</note> for then the infant begins to crave, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts much blood. For the blood pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after conception is diſcerned by a three-fold difference.<note place="margin">A three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold diſt n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of blood after conception.</note> The firſt and pureſt part of it the young one attracts for nouriſhment. The ſecond, leſs pure and thin, the matrix forceth upwards by certain veins to the breaſts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Venae mamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae.</hi> The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of milk.</note> where it becomes milk, by which the infant is nouriſhed ſo ſoon as it is born. The third, and more impure part of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57430:36"/>blood, remains in the matrix, and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out with the ſecundine, both in the birth, and after the birth: Hence it is that <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Aphor. lib. <hi>5.39</hi> &amp; <hi>52.</hi>
               </note> there is much affinity betwixt the flowers and the milk, ſince the one happeneth to be made out of the other. And <hi>Galen</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, by reaſon of this thing,<note place="margin">The infant hath more from the mother than the father.</note> elegantly adviſeth, that the infant hath more from the mother than from the father; for this reaſon, becauſe the ſeeds are firſt increaſed by the menſtruous blood, and then by theſe the infant is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nouriſhed in the womb; and again, being newly born, it is nouriſhed with milk: And, as roots have more nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment from the earth than the plant that bare them; (that is, from whence they came): ſo alſo infants receive more from the mother than from the father. And hence he ſaith that it comes to paſs, that ſo much more is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the mother, by how much more ſhe contributeth more towards gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a foetus in the womb</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A rule to know it.</note>If the infant be formed in 45 daies, it will ſtir in 90 daies, which is the middle time that it lies hid in the womb; for in the ninth moneth it will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57430:38"/>come forth, and make haſte to the birth; although females are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times born in the tenth moneth. And ſo much for the formation, increaſe, and perfection of the infant, according to the account of daies and times.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57430:38"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. III.</hi> How the infant doth in the womb the fifth, the ſixth, the ſeventh, and eighth moneth; and alſo of the difference of ſexes, and forms.</head>
            <p>AFter the third and fourth moneth the infant uſeth a more plentiful nouriſhment, by which it groweth more and more untill the time of birth ſhall come: Therefore it is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that when it is born in the ſixth moneth, it cannot in nature live; becauſe, though it be formed diſtinctly, yet it is not of its juſt perfection. But if it be born in the ſeventh moneth,<note place="margin">Why an infant born in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth may live.</note> it may eaſily live, becauſe then it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently perfect. And, whereas thoſe that are born in the eighth moneth can rarely live; whereas, ſuch as are born in the ſeventh moneth are often times
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57430:39"/>living, it is not without reaſon; for on the ſeventh moneth the infant is ever moving towards the birth, at which time, if it be ſtrong enough, it comes to the birth, but if not, it remaineth in the womb till it groweth ſtronger, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the other two moneths. After the motion at ſeven moneths end if it be not born, it removes it ſelf into ſome other place of the womb, and is ſo weakned by that motion, that ſhould it come to the birth in the following eighth moneth,<note place="margin">Two mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſigns by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</note> it cannot live by reaſon of that motion; and neither is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant indangered by this only, but by a double motion. The firſt is, that when after the motion of the ſeventh moneth, it is born the eighth moneth, (as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.) The next is, becauſe (by reaſon of the influence of the ſtars) every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth moneth produceth a dangerous and hurtful motion to the infant; for the Sun is ever ſtanding in an oppoſite ſign at that time, and becauſe the 8th. moneth is ever neareſt unto <hi>Saturn,</hi> an enemie to all that receive life.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57430:39"/>
            <p>And it is to be conceived,<note place="margin">The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the ſex. <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> Aphor. v. Book, and 48.</note> that the males are generated in the right ſide of the matrix; but females in the left, out of the left teſticle; for the right ſide, by reaſon of the Liver is hotter, but the left cooler; but principally the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant heat of ſeed is the cauſe of the generation of males.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of infants being like their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</note>And, becauſe males are ſometimes like their parents, is from the virtue of the ſeed, that the infant ſhould moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble thoſe whoſe ſeed is moſt in vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. But 'tis believed that the motion of the ſtars can do ſomewhat,<note place="margin">Stars have influence. The reaſon of handſome and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome children.</note> as when the ſeed is conceived under the aſpect of ſome good Planets, this makes an excellent form; but when under the aſpect of ſome untoward Planet, then it produceth an ugly ſhape, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beautiful form.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <hi>This figure ſheweth the Womb Anatomized and how the Infant lyeth in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The parts are deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the following page.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſs ſculpſit</hi>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:57430:42"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Of the due time and form of the Birth; and what are the cauſes of pains in Child-bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</head>
            <p>THe ninth moneth being now at hand, the nouriſhment of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant in the womb beginneth to fail, by reaſon of that bigneſs to which the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant is grown; or now being big, it requires much nouriſhment, which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot longer attract by the ſmall veins, and by the navil, it is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with great ſtruglings and force in the womb, inſomuch, as it breaketh the ligaments, the veins and coats in which the infant is involved (I mean the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundine) with the other coats, of which hereafter, and according to this figure, fitteth it ſelf toward the birth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What are the pains in Child-bearing?</note>By this indication Midwives and other women which ſometimes are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57430:43"/>unto pregnant women, may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the true pains of a woman in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, which in truth are nothing elſe but the force of the infant now perfect, by which they are enforced and toſſed, and with which they contend down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, that they may go forth; for the membrane being broken by that force, and the womb open, the humors begin to flow down, of which the infant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now freed, he preſently is ſenſible of the air, and being deſirous of this life, is turned toward the out-let of the matrix, with his head towards the orifice of the ſame: And this (ſee the precedent figure) is the form of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural birth;<note place="margin">A natural birth, what</note> if the head tend forth to the out let, with the hands drawn down to the ſides, and plac'd on the hips, as in the laſt figure. An unnatural birth (of which more at large, God willing, hereafter) may be ſaid to be where any of theſe conditions are wanting, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective; therefore let the Midwife take care that ſhe be timely prepared for the reception of any birth, with all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:57430:43"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus correctly presented for birth</figDesc>
                  <p>A Naturall Birth.</p>
                  <p>Croſs ſculy</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:44"/>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57430:44"/>conveniences, as with a fit ſtool,<note place="margin">The Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture.</note> a ſharp knife, aſtringent powder, a ſponge, ſwathes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> warm oyle of Lillies, with which ſhe may aptly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oint both the womb of the woman, and her own hands: but of that alſo more particularly hereafter. Let us now, in the next Section, make inquiry for the fitteſt and beſt Midwife, with whom we may diſcourſe. There is a good woman called Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia,</hi> who promiſed to undertake the office, and to be ſatisfied with directions. And ſee, here ſhe comes, and offers diſcourſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57430:45"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. V.</hi> A Dialogue between <hi>Eutrapelia</hi> the Midwife, and <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos</hi> the Doctor.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Sir, I underſtand you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after a woman that may make a fit Midwife; the employment being ſuch a neceſſary and publick good; I ſhould be willing (if your Worſhip, and other Learned Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans think me fit) to be ſerviceable in my generation, and to take upon me that employment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr. Philadelphos,</hi> Your name, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Sir, my name is <hi>Eutrapelia;</hi> and I am ſhe that laſt night promiſed to wait on you this morning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philad.</hi> Are you ſhe? Welcome Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia,</hi> your name beſpeaks you fit for the work, as being a well-bred woman; therefore give me leave to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57430:45"/>tell you what kind of perſon a Midwife ought to be, and that in the ſubſequent deſcription:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A good Midwife deſcribed.</note>The beſt Midwife is ſhe that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous, that knoweth letters, and having a good memory, is ſtudious, neat and cleanly over the whole body, healthful, ſtrong, and laborious, and well inſtructed in womens conditions, not ſoon angry, not turbulent, or haſty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Shiphrah Puah. Exod</hi> 1.17. and ver. 20 and 21.</note> unſober, unchaſte; but pleaſant, quiet, prudent; not covetous, but like the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Midwives, ſuch as fear God, that God may deal with them, and that the people may multiply and increaſe after their hands, and that the Lord may build them houſes.</p>
            <p>By this deſcription I tell you only how the beſt Midwife muſt be quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; let me hear from you ſomewhat of your experience and skill, that I may the better judge of your abilities, and approve of them. Firſt, then Mrs. let me know how women are delivered?</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a birthing stool</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>B. the Back of the Stoole</item>
                     <item>o o o o. the feete</item>
                     <item>a a. reſts for the hands</item>
                     <item>r r. the ring in ſhape like the Moone</item>
                     <item>c c c c. the Cloth round the ring to keepe out the Aire etc:</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Crofs ſculpſit</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note>℞. of Aloes, Frankincenſe, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons-blood, of each a drachm; of burnt Harts-horn, ſealed earth (called <hi>Terra ſigillata</hi>) fine flour, of each two drachms; of the wooll of Hares ſhread ſmall, half an ounce; of theſe make a fine powder.</p>
            <p>As to the waſhing of the child, and ſwathing, I need not give you any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, I ſuppoſe you take it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that moſt women underſtand that I only here ſhew you the ſhape of the ſtool I uſe, which, I hope, you will not diſapprove of, though all Midwives (nay few) have them, or uſe them.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Philadelphos,</hi> I like, Mrs. the uſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57430:48"/>of your ſtool, as being moſt uſeful, and eſpecially by reaſon of the skirt of cloth that uſually ought to be about<note place="margin">n="*" Of a black co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</note> it, to keep away the air, which gives me occaſion to give you one neceſſary admonition by the way.<note place="margin">A Caution.</note> Therefore let all Midwives take heed that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not their women that are in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to the cold air, but rather that they cover the privities with the ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine alſo whileſt it is yet hot, or elſe with warm clothes preſently after the birth. For, believe me, (neither is it only my opinion, but alſo the opinion of the moſt Learned Doctors) that there is nothing worſe to child-bearing women than the cold air,<note place="margin">Rodericus a Caſtro parte, <hi>2</hi> lib. <hi>4.</hi> Cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> becauſe that entring into the womb, the womb it ſelf is diſtended, waxeth cold, and ſwelleth, and its orifices are ſhut, from whence cometh the menſtruous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and thence ariſe grievous ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms, and often times death it ſelf. But as to the ſuppreſſion of them, and their cure, we ſhall (by divine aſſiſtance) treat more largely e're we leave this ſubject in hand.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:57430:49"/>
            <p>This precedent figure is the form of a child lying in the womb (according as cut in <hi>Tho. Bartholinus,</hi> in Page 197.) naked, and out of all its coats, both proper and common. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of it appears by the explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe letters in it, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AA Shews the parts of the <hi>Chorion</hi> diffected, and removed from their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place.</p>
            <p>B A portion of the membrane <hi>Amnios.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CC The membrane of the womb diffected<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>DD The <hi>placenta Uteri,</hi> or <hi>hepar ute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinum,</hi> being a fleſhy ſubſtance full of many veſſels, by which the infant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives its nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>E The varication of the Veſſels which makes up the navil ſtring.</p>
            <p>FF The navil ſtring by which the <hi>Umbili</hi> or veſſels are carried from the <hi>placenta</hi> to the navil.</p>
            <p>GG The infant, as it lyes perfect in the womb near the time of travel.</p>
            <p>H How the umbilical veſſels are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted into the navil of the infant.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:57430:49"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> Of the ſite of the child in the womb.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, how it lyeth in the womb.</note>THE infant in the womb lyeth altogether bowed and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted together, his knees to his belly, and head to his knees, the anckles being joyned to the buttocks, croſs-legg'd, his hands lifted up towards his head, on which he ſo leaneth his head, that his eyes ſeem to be fixed to the thumbs of his hands, the one placed on the temples, the other on the cheeks; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that white ſpots may be ſeen in the skin, as if they had been fretted the one againſt the other. The former part of the body tends towards the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er part of the belly of the mother (if it be a male) and the hinder part towards the back; but if it be a female, the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture is clean contrary. But the uſual poſture is as in this figure which goeth before.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:57430:50"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> Of difficult births, whether prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural, or whether they proceed from Cauſes external or internal.</head>
            <p>DIfficult births from external cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes may be either, firſt, from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive heat, diſſolving the ſtrength of the women; or ſecond, exceſſive cold, condenſing the womb;<note place="margin">Their can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> or third, from ſweet things, often applied to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils of the woman, that by ſmelling to ſweet things ſhe may recover her ſtrength and faintings; for ſweet ſmells do attract the womb upwards, and ſo render the birth more difficult.</p>
            <p>Difficult birth from internal cauſes may be either, firſt, from the woman; ſecond, from the womb; third, from the infant; fourth, from the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes of the womb. 1. From the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as when ſhe is too angry, too fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57430:50"/>or too modeſt; or if ſhe be in age above 40 years,<note place="margin">Women of above 40 years bring forth with difficulty.</note> from whence the muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the womb may be concluded to be dry, and ſo the leſs extenſible; or, when ſhe is ſo thick and fat, that the paſſages be narrow: Or, 2. From the womb it ſelf, as, when it is ſo ſmall, &amp; nature ſo weak and feeble that it cannot expell the birth: Or, if there be any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation,<note place="margin">Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The ſtone. Coſtive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Haemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoids.</note> or other preternatural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the privities, be it the ſtone, or haemorrhoid's, or extraordinary coſtive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; all which may ſo compreſs the womb with their weight, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expell the birth. 3. Is from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant it ſelf, as if it be of an unuſual big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of a great head, or a monſtrous birth, hydropical, gibbous, (that is crook-back'd) full of wind, dead in the womb, or lying there in a poſture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond nature; as when it comes over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart, with the feet forward, and not the head, or if the thigh before the head. 4 th. From the membranes of the womb, as when they are ſo forcibly broken by the child in the womb that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57430:51"/>the moyſture floweth thence, leaving the infant behind, that when the child ſhould come forth, that moyſture fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and ſo the membranes being dryer, maketh the birth the more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult; or when it is ſo firm and ſollid that it is broken with much difficulty, and ſo makes the labour the harder.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57430:51"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> Of the Schemes, Faſhions, and Figures of the birth lying in the womb, and how they are born, or may be born.</head>
            <p>THE poſtures of the infant in the womb are generally four: Firſt, they offer to come with their heads for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (which is the natural birth.) Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, with the feet forwards. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, overthwart. Fourthly, doubled; to all which the Midwives care and skill is required, but eſpecially in the three later. But chiefly very many po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and ſchemes have been obſerved, and are to be found by continuance of practiſe; for that child that comes with his head forward, ſometimes hath his head right as to the orifice of the matrix, but the reſt of the body crooked, and ſometimes overthwart: and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the infant pitcheth his head either in the former part from the orifice, or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57430:52"/>backward, or comes crooked; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo theſe ſchemes are without any tye as to the bottom of the matrix, and ſometimes with it; ſometimes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it puts forth one hand, or both, ſo as that they are twiſted above the head: ſometimes it cometh forward, with its feet aſunder, and thoſe fixed in the parts of the womb; ſometimes the feet being doubled, it endeavours to come forth with the knees forward; ſometimes it is ſo doubled, that it ſhews forth its lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle buttocks like one that is ſitting; or contrarily may be ſo doubled, that you may find the ſoles of the feet joyned to the head in the orifice of the matrix; but thoſe that lye o'rethwart, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lye on one ſide, and ſometimes with the face upwards, and ſometimes downwards: But if there be twins, then that which preſenteth it ſelf faireſt, muſt be laid hold on, and the other put back. As to all which, the next 15 or 16 Sections will not only furniſh with ſchemes, but with directions. Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to having deſcribed the Midwife and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57430:52"/>her office, together with the ſite of the infant in the womb, as natural; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with difficult births in general, and their cauſes. It is reaſonable, (good Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia</hi>) that we diſcourſe of praeternatural births becauſe thoſe bring the greateſt danger with them, both to the mother and infant.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. IX.</hi> Scheme the firſt. Of praeternatural Births.</head>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> DR. <hi>Philad.</hi> Courteous Mrs. <hi>Eutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelia,</hi> If you perceive a child come with his feet forwards, and the hands drawn downwards to the thighs, according to this next enſuing form, How will you deliver the woman?</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:57430:53"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> In this, I will take care to be furniſhed with Oyles,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> and convenient liniments, and only to help the coming forth of the infant, by anointing and cheriſhing it, leſt it go back again, but that it may come forth the ſame way as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57430:53"/>it began. But firſt of all I ſhall take care, that both arms of the infant ſo ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed downwards, be ſo ſecured by me, that the infant may not have power to draw them back again, but that I may compell it to come forth, after this very ſame manner: But if the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant breaking forth after this manner, and by reaſon of its bigneſs as well as his arms drawn down, be ſo ſtreightned by the narrowneſs of the matrix, that of it ſelf it cannot wholly come to the birth; then the womb of the woman is to be annointed with oyle of Lillies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oyles.</hi> Opus est Elleboro.</note> or ſweet Almonds, and ſome ſneezing Powder of Hellebor, &amp;c. blowed up into her noſe, to help the ſending forth of the birth, and the womb gently to be compreſſed with both hands, that it tend not upwards, but downwards, as it ought, untill it comes forth entirely.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="section">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:57430:54"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. X.</hi> Scheme the Second.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> But, tell me, I pray, Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia;</hi> What if an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant come with the feet forward, and the hands lifted up above the head, and not drawn downwards to the thighs, (as in the following ſigure) what courſe will you take with moſt ſafety?</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57430:54"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Sir, I am not at all to receive it ſo lying,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> except the infant be very ſmall and little, and the matrix ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive, and open, that it may be hoped a ſafe delivery, both to the woman and to the child; neither muſt I receive it
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57430:55"/>before the matrix and the infant be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently anointed. But it were much better to thruſt back the infant into the womb, and to turn it to the right form, which may be done after this manner. Let the woman lye on her back upon a bed, with her buttocks raiſed higher, and her head lower; which done, I muſt ſwathe her belly toward the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff gently, that I may drive back the infant again into the womb, by which means it may give an occaſion of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth in another form; but above all, I muſt take care to turn the face of the infant toward the back of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and then I muſt lift up the buttocks and thighes of the infant toward the navil of the mother, that it may haſten toward a lawful birth: and there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a ſafer experiment in this caſe, (as I conceive) which is alſo moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in ſuch births as come praeternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="section">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:57430:55"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XI.</hi> Scheme the Third.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PHiladelphos;</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> I pray forſooth tell me, If the infant happen to come forth but with one foot, and the arms let down to the ſides, but the other foot turned backwards; How will you help?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> In this caſe, Sir, I muſt not trouble the woman, but muſt bring her to her bed again, and ſo by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of other women, bend her, and turn her after the ſame manner as was formerly propoſed, putting back alſo the other foot into the womb; which done, ſhe muſt often tumble her ſelf upon her bed, till I find the infant in ſome meaſure turned, and the woman brought fitly to her labour, and helped with all means poſſibly to be uſed. And this kind of toſſing and tumbling may be uſed in all births, where the infant
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:57430:56"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
               </figure> appears after an unapt manner: In the mean time, when there is need, ſhe ought to be refreſhed with ſuch Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal means as may be proper. But if it ſhall happen that either by the rolling to and fro of the woman, or my indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:57430:56"/>that the foot ſo bent back come right to the birth; then I muſt take care that (laying hold of the arms otherwiſe drawn downwards toward the ſides) I bring the infant handſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out, ſo as is anſwered in the firſt Chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XII.</hi> Scheme the Fourth.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PHiladelphos;</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>4</label> If an infant lye a-croſs on the one ſide, or on its back, with the hands and feet up; how will you help it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrapelia;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Sir, In this caſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, I muſt not trouble the woman, nor expect the infant to be born ſo ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which without ſome way of turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is impoſſible. Therefore I am to take care that I reduce it to the true form of a natural birth, by lifting up
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57430:57"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
               </figure> the buttocks, and directing the head to the birth; and if this courſe ſucceed not, to ſee that by often rolling upon the bed, as aforeſaid, the infant return to its right form of lying.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:58"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="section">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:57430:58"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XIII.</hi> Scheme the Fifth.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PHiladel.</hi> Tell me, Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>5</label> What if the infant happen to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to the birth with his arms and legs diſtorted and crooked, according to this figure; How then will you help?</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:57430:59"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> As things ſo ſtand, Sir, I muſt not endeavour the birth of the child, but muſt bring her from the ſtool to the bed, where I muſt preſs back the womb as before-ſaid, or muſt deſire her to roul her ſelf about, till the infant
<pb facs="tcp:57430:59"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:57430:60"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:57430:60"/>is turned to a more commodious po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture: And if this courſe prevail not, I muſt endeavour to joyn both feet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and, if poſſible, muſt bring down the hands ſo to the ſides, that I may direct it to the birth. But the ſafeſt way is, that it be converted, in the womb, to its right poſture.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XIV.</hi> Scheme the Sixth.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> Tell me, Midwife, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>6</label> what if the infant fall down with both the knees bent, and the hands hanging down to the thighs; How will you go to work?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Here, Doctor,<note place="margin">Arſwer.</note> I muſt with my right hand lift up both knees up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, till the feet happen to come forth foremoſt, then with my left hand I muſt lay hold on the feet, and with my right hand keep the hands to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57430:61"/>ſides, and encourage the infant toward the birth. But if this way be not thought ſafe enough, I muſt bring the woman to the bed, where lying in ſuch a poſture as before, ſhe ſhall ſo roul her ſelf up and down, till the infant come to a better and more commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous poſture.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XV.</hi> Scheme the Seventh.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>7</label> But, Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia,</hi> What if the infant come out ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily with one hand, and the other hand down towards the ſide, and the feet ſtretched out ſtreight into the womb, according to this figure; How will you receive it?</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:57430:61"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> May it pleaſe you, Sir,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> I am not at all to receive it ſo, nor to ſuffer it to proceed farther toward the birth; but muſt bring her to the bed, where her head muſt lye lower than her but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks; then I muſt ſwath her belly
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57430:62"/>gently, that the infant may fall back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into the womb: but if it fall not back of its own accord, I muſt put in my hand, and preſs back the ſhoulders, and muſt reduce the arm that hanged out to the ſide, that it may be diſpoſed of to a natural form in the womb, and ſo may come forth eaſily.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XVI.</hi> Scheme the Eighth.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>8</label> But, Mrs, Suppoſe the infant come forth with both hands ſtretched forth above the head, and the feet ſtreight ſtretched into the womb, which is here figured, and is much more dangerous than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer?</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:57430:62"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> 'Tis true, Sir,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> this poſture is much more dangerous than the former; but I ſhall take all the care I can to bring back again this birth into the womb wholly. And firſt of all, I ſhall annoint my hands, and the womb of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:57430:63"/>woman, with oyles for this purpoſe, (for this requires no ſmall labour) then, if poſſible, with my other hand ſhall drive it back ſo by the ſhoulders, that it may wholly fall back into the womb: And again, leſt the infant ſhould return to the ſame form of birth, I muſt put in my hands, and bring down the arms of the infant to the ſides, and by that means bring it to the form of a natural birth. If this courſe take not, I muſt bring the woman to the bed, where, after ſhe hath lain quiet a while, I muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed after the ſame manner as I have before delivered: and if this alſo be to no purpoſe, and that it neither be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to another form, ſhe muſt be brought to the ſtool; and the womb, by the help of the women that are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, muſt be depreſſed on both ſides, and downwards: And (my hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing annointed as before-ſaid, together with the womb, and both the arms as they come) I muſt do what I can to joyn them together, and ſo receive it as it comes forth. And in this birth, there
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:57430:63"/>is the leſs danger, if that I or any other Midwife do our duties with all poſſible diligence, and in caſe the infant be not too weak.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XVII.</hi> Scheme the ninth.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PHiladel.</hi> But I beſeech you, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>9</label> Mrs. <hi>Eutrap.</hi> How will you deliver a woman of a child that falls down with its buttocks forward, and the hands ſpread over the head, according to this figure?</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:57430:64"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Here,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Sir, I muſt annoint my hand as above-ſaid, and putting it up, muſt lift up the fundament of the child, and turn the head to the Birth. But, in this caſe I muſt not make too much haſte, leſt it fall into ſome worſer form;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:57430:64"/>neither is it poſſible that a child ſhould be ſo born, without great loſs to the mother and the infant; therefore, if it cannot be turned with the hand, ſhe muſt be brought to the bed, where, if ſhe be very weak, ſhe may be refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with convenient meats and cordials, and then often proceeded with as is ſaid before, untill the infant ſhall come to a more commodious form of birth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XVIII.</hi> Scheme the tenth.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philad.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>10</label> But ſometimes (Mrs.) it happens that it offers it ſelf with its ſhoulders forwards, and the head turned backwards, but the feet and hands lifted up, as in the enſuing fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure; How will you help here?</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:57430:65"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> In this caſe, Sir; I muſt in the firſt place move backward the ſhoulders of the infant, that it may firſt appear with the head forward; and this may eaſily be done, becauſe the ſhoulders being but a little up, the head
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:57430:65"/>of it ſelf will fall down to the orifice of the womb, as being neareſt to it. But if there muſt be any other way at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, ſhe muſt be brought back to the bed, and then ſo ſtirred and rouled, and uſed according to thoſe directions formerly hinted.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XIX.</hi> Scheme the Eleventh.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> Mrs, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>11</label> I fear I trouble you with many Queſtions; be pleaſed to ſatisfie me in this, and four or five more, and I ſhall forbear. What then if the infant incline to the birth with the hands and feet together, as if it ſtood upon all four, with the back upward into the womb, (as in this figure) What, I ſay, will you do?</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:57430:66"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Here,<note place="margin">Anſwer</note> Sir, I muſt take care, leſt ſome danger happen from this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult and unſhapely figure; therefore I muſt do thus. I muſt ſo move up the feet of the infant, that I may handle the head, and do what I can to direct that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:57430:66"/>firſt to the birth: I muſt alſo move up the arms, leſt of their own accord they fall down to the ſides of the womb. And if this way ſucceed not, ſhe muſt be brought back to the bed, and the ſame means uſed for the turning of the infant as hath been formerly deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XX.</hi> Scheme the Twelfth.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PHiladel.</hi> Sometimes, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>12</label> Mrs. it falls out, that (contrary to the former ſhape) the infant falls down upon its breaſt, with the hands and feet caſt backward into the womb, as in this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure; what will you do in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition?</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:57430:67"/>
            <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Truly, Sir, this caſe is the moſt dangerous of all hitherto propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Firſt, therefore, I muſt carefully annoint both my hands, and alſo the womb of the woman; which done, I muſt enquire after the arms of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:57430:67"/>and lay hold of them ſo, till I can lay hold of the head alſo, and with all care hold it ſo faſt, that I may direct the head firſt to the birth; next I muſt diſpoſe of them to the ſides; for this being done, the birth will come forth the ſooner, and with leſs danger; but if this ſucceed not, it will be ſafeſt to bring the woman to the bed, and to proceed as formerly ſhewed; that, if perhaps, by this kind of delay, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant may accommodate it ſelf to a more fit poſture for the birth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXI.</hi> Scheme the thirteenth.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> There being the ſame reaſon in twins as in a ſingle birth, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>13</label> except that the ſingle birth is natural, and the twins not ſo; certainly the ſame method muſt be obſerved (Mrs.) Tell me then, if there be two or more,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:57430:68"/>and all come fair with their heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the birth; What is to be done?</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with twin foetuses in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Here,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Sir, I muſt obſerve that which lyeth readieſt and fitteſt in the womb, and firſt receive that, and not to let the other go till the firſt is
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:57430:68"/>born, leſt it turn into another ſhape by ſliding back again into the womb; but the one being born, I muſt preſently lay hold on the other. Now, this birth will be eaſier, and without danger, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the firſt birth hath made the way for the ſecond ſo plain, that it may come forth without any difficulty at all. But in this birth I muſt take care that I bring forth the after-burden timely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,<note place="margin">After-burden.</note> leſt that the womb, being freed from her infants, preſently fall down, and ſo keep in the ſecundine or after-burden with great danger.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXII.</hi> Scheme the fourteenth.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> But, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>14</label> Mrs. What if there be twins, and they both come praeternaturally with their feet forward, as in this figure; what courſe will you take?</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:57430:69"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with twin foetuses in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> This birth,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Sir, is dangerous enough, and yet it is to be mended by the prudence of a diſcreet Midwife. Wherefore, I muſt anoint the womb of the woman, that the paſſages may be the eaſier for the infant; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:57430:69"/>done, I muſt take care to lay hold of the arms of one of them, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them down to the ſides, ſecure them ſo, that I may lightly promote the head to the birth; and the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born, I muſt preſently proceed with the other after the ſame manner: but if I can lay hold of neither of their arms, ſo that there is no good hopes of a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py birth, I muſt have recourſe to the former method; if at leaſt the infants may come into the world by that pains and converſion which is wrought upon the bed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXIII.</hi> Scheme the fifteenth.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>15</label> I come now to the laſt praeternatural birth of twins. If then there be twins, (theſe form being compound as of a natural and praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural birth) the one coming down
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:57430:70"/>with the feet, what is to be done in this caſe?</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with twin foetuses in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Where infants offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves after this manner; I muſt firſt bring forth that which preſents it ſelf with a natural form, and muſt move
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:57430:70"/>up the other, that is with the feet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and if poſſible, cauſe it ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into the womb, that that birth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may be diſpoſed of to a natural birth; but if it cannot be converted to be in a better poſture, I muſt lay hold preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the hands, and encourage it to the birth. But it were ſafer that this ſhould be brought to a natural form; to which end I muſt diligently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour it, by anointing, directing, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, tumbling and rouling the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, leſt perhaps the womb be hurt by the form of ſuch an unnatural birth, and the privities ſwell with<note place="margin">n="*" See the page to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the later end of the fifth Section.</note> wind, from whence the birth cannot come forth without danger, or be hindred too long: All which danger may with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident care be avoided, or at the leaſt very much corrected and amended.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="section">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:57430:71"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXIV.</hi> Scheme the ſixteenth.</head>
            <p>DR. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>16</label> 
               <hi>Philadelphos;</hi> Courteous Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia,</hi> I have hitherto trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled you with many Queſtions, that I might not only be ſure of your abilities, but alſo give teſtimony of your ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, if need require. I have now on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one Queſtion more, and then I have done, as to theſe poſtures and ſchemes: And this, though the laſt, ſurely is a miraculous poſture. What if the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant be ſo involved in the womb (the head and the neck being of ſuch a length) that it is ſo bent back, that the face lyeth betwixt the buttocks, the right hand to the left region of the reins, but the left hand to the knee of the ſame ſide; the right legg being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſs the left, in form of the letter X, and both leggs bent up toward the breaſt?</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:57430:71"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a uterus with foetus in an abnormal birth position</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Worthy Dr. This caſe is the hardeſt of any that hitherto you have propounded to me; and though it may never fall out to be ſo in one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt 5000, yet (becauſe, in your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the beſt Midwife, you tell
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:57430:72"/>me that a Midwife muſt have a good memory) I remember a learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, not long ſince acquainted me with ſuch a poſture, which he told me he had from the hands of an expert<note place="margin">n="*" Guli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>britius Hildanus, Century, <hi>the ſixth; Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Lxiv.</hi>
               </note> Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon and Phyſitian, whoſe wife al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo was an expert Midwife; and the courſe the Midwife took in ſuch a caſe, he told me was this, which muſt ſerve alſo for my anſwer, becauſe I think there cannot be a better. After the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had been eight daies in labour, and given over by all Midwives as deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, being in a violent Fever, with no throws, but very weak, and (by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of hot medicines given to expel the birth, and ſtrong wines given to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the ſpirits) thoſe humors that uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally accompany the infant had ſo flown out,<note place="margin">Blood and water.</note> that the genitals were ſo dry and cloſed, that they would ſcarce admit the probation of two fingers. This me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod was uſed: Firſt, inſtead of wine, ſhe gave her good ſtore of Almond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milk; and becauſe her belly was very coſtive, ſhe gave her Clyſters; and to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:57430:72"/>keep up her ſpirits ſhe gave her Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, (of which in their order.) She laid plaiſters to her hand-wriſts, and anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the whole region of the belly, hips, loins, the rump-bone, and privities,<note place="margin">Os ſacrum.</note> with anodyne Oyles, with emollient and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxing Unguents; and then ſhe made a triangular bagg ſtuff'd with emolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and relaxing herbs, boyled in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, according to this deſcription, (and of which more hereafter.)</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:57430:73"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a triangular bag used as a hot compress during labour</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>It is of ſuch a bigneſs, as that it might cover the lower part of the belly, and the privities, and with tapes fitted to the corners was applyed hot, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued on ſome hours; after which, though her hand were well anointed,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:57430:73"/>ſhe could ſcarce thruſt in the top of her finger into the orffice of the womb, the womb was ſo cloſed,<note place="margin">Called the <hi>Os pubis.</hi>
               </note> and the infant ſo depreſſed toward the ſhare-bone, by reaſon of the precedent throws and pangs. But at length, when with much labour and induſtry the genitals were ſomewhat dilated, that ſhe could get in her fingers farther, ſhe found the loyns and the right hand of the child firſt offer it ſelf to the birth: that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe might correct this monſtrous and ſo inverted poſture of the infant ſo doubled and twiſted, and either per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the head or the feet to come for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſhe uſeth the beſt of her skill, but to little purpoſe, the genitals were ſo narrow and ſtreight. But yet not giving off her endeavours, ſhe did deliver her within eight hours after ſhe came to her aſſiſtance; but the child was dead.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Phila.</hi> Mrs. You give a very good account of an expert Midwives pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, which you may follow with ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, expecting the ſuccceſs from Heaven;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:57430:74"/>but it is no wonder the child ſhould be ſtill-born, (as you phraſe it;) for being ſo turned and doubled, the child muſt of neceſſity be ſtrangled in the womb.</p>
            <p>Having thus run through births, as well natural as praeternatural, I ſhall give you the reaſon (and that in my own opinion) why theſe births are of ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious &amp; different poſtures in the womb, obſerving not alwaies the ſame poſture: and 'tis thus.<note place="margin">The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of theſe different poſtures.</note> Becauſe the infant ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in water, and moving it ſelf, ſometimes this way, ſometimes that way, and is bent and tumbled ſeveral wates; inſomuch, that ſometimes it is ſtrangely entangled with its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil-cord, which I am confident you have ſeen in your own experience of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="section">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:57430:74"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXV.</hi> Of a Mola.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> We have hitherto,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> Mrs, diſcourſed of births natural and praeternatural; there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more not like theſe, but often with them, and without them, which Phyſitians call a <hi>Mola,</hi> but you call it a falſe Conception: I pray, Mrs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what is that <hi>Mola,</hi> or falſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſwers A <hi>Mola,</hi> or falſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, what.</note>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> A <hi>Mola,</hi> (Mr. Doctor,) ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally called a falſe conception, is a hard inform tumor, full of pores, (like ſo many ugly eyes) ſcarce to be cut by a knife, of a ſtony ſubſtance to touch, and round, appearing ſometimes at the entrance of the womb, ſometimes over the whole womb, and is generally thought (by the<note place="margin">n="*" Fernelius, lib. <hi>vii,</hi> cap. de faemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</note> Learned'ſt Doctors) to be begotten by the woman her ſelf without the help of a man. <hi>(Qualis &amp;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:57430:75"/>quanta ea ſit vis declarant rudiores moloe quas faeminae quando<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> proprii duntaxat ſeminis vi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fran. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſii con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum, lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> in fine. Ex pauco ſemine ea<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> impure.</note> 
               <hi>nullo viri concubitu concipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt;)</hi> And ſo another Dr. in theſe words (I beg your pardon, Mrs. that I am enforced to uſe authorities in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine) (ſome affirming that it cannot be without the ſeed of the man.)</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Valeſius,</hi> as before quoted.</note>
               <hi>Hinc cognoſces, quod faemina ſaepe ex ſe ſola ſolet utero concipere; foetus ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ad perfectionem nunquam perducitur; ex his tamen imperfectis conceptionibus quae dicuntur, molae matricis generantur &amp; informia carnis fruſta.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inanimate, becauſe not generated by two,<note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>et affectu quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> without the help of a man (I ſay) by the force of her own ſeed, mixing it ſelf with much menſtruous blood, reteined in the womb, which by immoderate heat it changeth into the ſhape of fleſh, and that altogether prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural, as is the ſtone in the bladder, and in the fingers of gouty perſons, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Philadel.</hi> Well, Mrs. ſince 'tis ſo (as in truth it is; tell me, I pray,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57430:75"/>wherein it differs from a true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception?<note place="margin">The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a true and falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> It may, Sir, be like a true Conception in three reſpects, yet differ in ſix. As firſt, 'Tis true that a falſe conception ſtoppeth the monethly terms as doth the true.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The belly alſo doth ſwell, and the breaſts grow big.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is an alteration both in the colour and appetite; but yet they differ in theſe ſix enſuing following waies; as,</p>
            <p>Firſt, A falſe conception hath no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary nor periodical motion, neither doth it ſtir from ſide to ſide, except it be preſſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In a falſe conception the belly is harder, and the feet are much more ſwelled.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The woman is more heavy and unweeldy, and not ſo nimble as with a true conception.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The breaſts ſwell not ſo much as in a true conception.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The whole body grows ſoft,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57430:76"/>and conſumes away in a falſe concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but not ſo in a true.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, a falſe conception may be moved in three moneths, but the child ſtirreth not till after three moneths, or uſually in the fourth moneth: And again, the birth of an infant never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the eleventh moneth, whereas a falſe conception may continue for four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years,<note place="margin">A <hi>Mola</hi> may lye 14 years.</note> or as long as they live.</p>
            <p>Moreover, there may be a Tympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie cauſed by air included in the womb.<note place="margin">Tympany, what. <hi>Hydrops u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terinus.</hi>
               </note> Or elſe there may be a Dropſie, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the many humors contained in the womb, both which may give a falſe ſuppoſition of being with child; but theſe alſo are eaſily diſtinguiſh'd from a falſe conception. A Tympanie may be moved from place to place, but not the other: A Tympanie will ſound, if lightly ſtrucken, but not the other; and a Dropſie, cauſed by thoſe many humors as aforeſaid, will ſhew ſome marks, being depreſſed with the fingers, whereas a <hi>Mola</hi> is hard, and yieldeth not to the pulſation or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:57430:76"/>of the fingers. And laſtly, in both theſe moſt commonly the thighs ſwell, but in a falſe conception or <hi>mola</hi> the thighs wither, and are leſſer. Now having diſcourſed of theſe things, Sir; if you pleaſe, in the next place, let us diſcourſe of the ſecundine, or after-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Philadel.</hi> I ſhall, Mrs. very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="section">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:57430:77"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXVI.</hi> Of the Secundine, or After-burden.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadelphos,</hi> Come then, Mrs. if you pleaſe, tell me what the Secundine is.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">After-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, what.</note> 
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> The Secundine is that in which the infant lyeth in the womb, and may be called a ſecond houſe, or covering, made by the womb for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle of the infant; and it hath with it three membranes; but how Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians name them, I know not.</p>
            <p>Dr. I will inform you then, if you pleaſe, with their names and uſes; and deſcribe them to you in theſe two figures following, which are explained by letters alſo, as may appear.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>The explanation of the firſt Figure.</head>
                  <item>BBB Signifies that part of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundine</hi> called the <hi>Chorion,</hi> which is the
<pb facs="tcp:57430:77"/>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of the placenta</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:57430:78"/>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:57430:78"/>prop of all the veſſels of the young one.</item>
                  <item>CCC Denotes the branches of the Umbilical veins and arteries diſperſed through the <hi>Chorion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>EEE The membrane called <hi>Amnios,</hi> and is the thinneſt of all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes, and is white, ſoft, and ſhining, with few (and thoſe very ſmall) veins and arteries diſperſed among the folds; and this is the very next coat to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, and is the receptacle for ſweat and urine; that membrane called <hi>Allantois</hi> not to be found in men, though an <hi>Urachus</hi> be to be found.</item>
                  <item>DD Denotes all the veſſels meeting about the navil, by which the infant is nouriſhed.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:57430:79"/>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>P. Q Denotes the membrane cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Amnios,</hi> and is the firſt that invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the infant.</item>
                  <item>RRRR The Liver,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>RRRR.</hi> Epar ute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinum, <hi>or,</hi> Placenta uteri.</note> or cake of the womb, or after-burden, by which the infant receives nouriſhment, and this is faſtned to the womb.</item>
                  <item>SS The inward and outward veins.</item>
                  <item>m.m.m. The Umbilical vein, with its branches diſperſed into the after-burden, by which the child is nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and upon which it lyeth, as upon a pillow, though in the <hi>Amnios</hi> it ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth as in a bath.</item>
                  <item>VV How all the veſſels meet about the navil.</item>
                  <item>b.b.b Denotes the infant newly born, annexed to the <hi>ſecundine,</hi> the navil-ſtring not cut.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a new-born infant attached to the placenta</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chorion</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amnios</hi>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>v <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The firſt Galea.</note>The firſt membrane is called <hi>Amni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os,</hi> and this membrane covers the infant from the head to foot; inſomuch, that part of it ſticks to the head of the infant when it is born, which they call a hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, though this is not alwaies, being left behind with the <hi>ſecundine</hi> in diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult labours: this is ſo called from its ſoftneſs and thinneſs; others reſemble it to white paper, or a ſhirt, and is the thinneſt of all, in which is found great plenty of humors, cauſed of urine and ſweat, in which the infant ſwimmeth as in a bath, and lyeth ſo eaſie and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, leſt it ſhould fall foul againſt thoſe neighbouring parts that are harder; and beſides that, when the membrane is broken in the birth, this water break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:57430:81"/>out, may make the paſſages by the neck of the womb more plain and ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery for the infant; and this mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane alſo is every where concluded within the ſecond,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</note> which is called <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion,</hi> becauſe it wraps the infant like a ring; and this immediately compaſſeth the former, to which it is joyned as it were in a round figure, like to a cake, whoſe inward and hollow part it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and involves, and doth extend it ſelf to its dimenſions, and can ſcarce be ſeparated from it, but doth firmly knit and bear up the veſſels of the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden,<note place="margin">Epar Ute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinum.</note> which immediately ſticks to the womb by a certain fleſhy maſs that is formed, being round, and of ſomewhat a ruddy colour, not compaſſing the whole infant, by reaſon of innumerous ſprings of veins and arteries by which the blood is inter-woven, as if it were poured in, and by which the infant is nouriſhed. This towards the infant is ſmooth, but that part which is towards that fleſhy round maſs, is rougher.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:57430:81"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Placenta Uteri, <hi>or</hi> Epar Ute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinum.</note>This round fleſhy ſubſtance is called the liver of the womb, or the cake of the womb; which, having (a <hi>paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyma</hi>) ſuch a ſubſtance as the liver hath, no wonder if it ſhould make and prepare blood for the nouriſhment of the infant. On that ſide towards the womb it is rough, and unequal, like clefts in a bak'd cake; and being cut in this part, it ſheweth an infinite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of fibres, which, if you trace, they will bring you to the orifice of the veins themſelves. And, although there be twins, or more, yet there is but one <hi>placenta;</hi> for into one <hi>placenta</hi> ſo many navil-ſtrings are inſerted (in divers places) as there are young ones;<note place="margin">Embryones.</note> though it may differ as to the bigneſs, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the body and condition of the infant, yet the ground is ſtill the ſame in the diameter.<note place="margin">The uſe of the <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centa.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> The third. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The uſe ſerves as a ſupport of the unibilical veſſels, for which it ſerves as a pillar; it is alſo called <hi>(ſecundae)</hi> the ſecundine. The third is called <hi>Allantoides;</hi> 'tis a coat betwixt the <hi>Chorion</hi> and <hi>Amnios;</hi> 'tis
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:57430:82"/>difficulty. Be it as it will, whereſoever theſe make but the leaſt ſtay, I muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, all that I can, to bring them forth: for when they are deteined lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than their due time, they cauſe bad ſymptoms,<note place="margin">Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms.</note> as a horrible ſtench, which fumes up to the ſtomach, heart, liver, midriff, and ſo conſequently to the brain; from whence ariſeth great pains in the head, at the heart, decay of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, faintings, ſwounings, often Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, cold Sweats, Apoplexies, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilepſies, ſometimes Gangrenes, and often death it ſelf: but of this Cure, hereafter, Sir, I ſhall beg your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philadel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> Mrs. you ſhall have it at your pleaſure; you anſwer expertly; tell me now how they muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded out?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> I ſhall, Sir; I muſt firſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oint my left hand with convenient oyles, and after I have laid hold of it, muſt not violently draw it away,<note place="margin">Secundine, how to be brought away.</note> nor yet force it directly downward, leſt I draw down the womb and all together;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:57430:82"/>but I muſt ſhake it lightly and gently to and fro, till I perſwade it to follow my intention; and whileſt they are thus reteined, I muſt refreſh her with Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles,<note place="margin">A Caudle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broth.</note> or Panatells, wherein the yelks of Eggs in Wine, with ſome Saffron and Cinnamon ſtrewed; or broth of a Hen or Capon, with mace, ſaffron, and cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon boyled in it. As to other means, where the danger is more, I think it ever beſt and ſafeſt to conſult with learned Phyſitians, or with experienc'd Ladies, whoſe Cloſets are furniſhed with choice praeſcriptions which they have had from Doctors, in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philadel.</hi> But,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> Mrs. we have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcourſed of Births, natural, and praeternatural, with their reſpective ſchemes. Tell me now,<note place="margin">A dead child, how delivered, and how of a <hi>Mola.</hi>
               </note> how you will deliver a woman of a dead child? and how of a falſe Conception, or <hi>Mola?</hi> Eſpecially, where no pains or throws are, which are moſt commonly occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the motion and force of the child only alive (as hath been ſhewed
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:57430:83"/>in the 21th. Page, and 4th. Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Here, Sir, is great danger and difficulty. I have, by Gods bleſſing, with ſafety to the women, delivered them of many a dead child, and of a <hi>Mola,</hi> or falſe Conception, alſo; and believe the method of curing one of them, will ſerve to cure the other; as I have been informed by learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians; but where Chirurgical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or other Phyſical means muſt be uſed, I ever recommend ſuch a caſe to learned Phyſitians, and Chirurgeons, expert in Anatomy, both for aſſiſtance and direction.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="section">
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:57430:83"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXVII.</hi> Of the ſigns of Conception in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and the different Sexes in particular.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadelphos.</hi> Good Mrs. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapelia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> vouchſafe me your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations about Conceptions,<note place="margin">Signs of Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and let me underſtand what are the ſigns of Conception in general; and what ſigns diſtinguiſh the Sexes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Although, Sir,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> 'tis hard to know whether a woman hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived yea or no, yet it may be conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured by many experienced Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; as, for inſtance,</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is thought a credible ſign of Conception, if a woman either the tenth day after coition, or ſooner, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, by reaſon of any humors, any of her terms, be they whites, or reds.<note place="margin">Stopping of the courſes no ſure ſign.</note> And, though the ſtopping of thoſe be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a ſign, yet that fails often, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:57430:84"/>it may be as well before concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as after. But, waving this, let us find out other marks and prognoſticks of a true conception, gathered from the ſtate and condition of the woman her ſelf, being ſeriouſly examined from head to foot.</p>
            <p>Secondly; pains and giddineſs in in the head, and a miſt over the ſight, if they meet together, theſe portend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the apples of the eyes are leſſened, the eyes ſwell, and become ſwarthy; the veins of the eyes grow red, and are full with blood; the eyes fink, the eye-lids are remiſs; divers colours are ſeen in the eyes, and are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in a looking-glaſs; the veins betwixt the eyes and the noſe are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid with blood, and are ſeen clearer; the veins under the tongue are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what greeniſh.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the cheſt is warm, and the back cold.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the veins and arteries are turgid, and the pulſe eaſier; the veins
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:57430:84"/>in the breaſt are firſt black, then either yellow or blew.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The breaſts grow big, and hard with pain; the nipple grows red; if ſhe drinketh that which is cold, ſhe feels cold in her breaſt.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, there is a great loathing of meat and drink, and deſtruction of the natural appetite, with longings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter various meats, with an abſurd ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, a continual vomiting, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſtomach, ſower belchings, loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of wine, an inordinate pulſation of the heart, ſudden joy, and after that, as ſudden grief; pains about the navil,<note place="margin">Invicem cedunt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas.</note> heavineſs about the loins, ſwelling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the bottom of the belly; inward pricking in the body; chilneſs of the outward parts, after coition; reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſeed ſeven daies after co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation; about the beginning of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception a ſhooting pain about the back and belly. The courſes are ſtop'd; for thoſe veins from which they flow carry the blood (through certain holes that are at the end of them) for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin">Acetabule,</note>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:57430:85"/>of the infant by the navil; and part of it is conveyed upwards into the breaſts,<note place="margin">Milk, how generated.</note> and there is prepared for milk.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, the thighs ſwell with pains, but the body is weaker, and the face pale.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, the belly is coſtive, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the compreſſure of the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines. The urine is white, with a cloud ſwimming at the top, wherein are to be ſeen many atomes, like thoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in the beams of the ſun: but, when in the firſt moneth many of theſe ſink to the bottom, and the veſſel in which it is, being ſhaken, it ſeems to be drawn out like to wooll. In the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter moneths the urine is reddiſh, or yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, it becomes blackiſh, with a red cloud at the top. I will here-with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to you two experiments,<note place="margin">Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> by which it may be known whether or no a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath conceived.<note place="margin">Firſt.</note> And the firſt is this; Stop up a womans urine three daies in a urinal, at the end of which ſtrain it (or, rather drop it through fine
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:57430:85"/>linnen) and if ſhe hath conceived, you ſhall ſee little creatures like to lice; if theſe be red, 'tis a token of a male;<note place="margin">Signs of a Male.</note> but if white, they portend a female. But this is ſaid to be ſure;<note place="margin">Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> If a womans u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine be put in a braſs Baſon, and ſtand there one night; if you put into it a bright needle, if ſhe hath conceived, that needle will be beſpeckled with red ſpots; but, if otherwiſe, it will be ruſty all over.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Philadel.</hi> Theſe, 'tis true,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> may be promiſcuous ſigns of Conception. But, Mrs. how know you the Sex, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther male, or female?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrapelia.</hi> By theſe ſigns, Sir,<note place="margin">Anſwer. Firſt</note> uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; as Firſt, If ſhe hath conceived a male, the right eye moves oftner, and is better, as to its native colour, than the left. The belly is ſharper about the navil.<note place="margin">Second</note> The right breaſt groweth tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid before the left, and the nipple is ſooner changed.<note place="margin">Thirdly.</note> The milk increaſeth ſooner, and if it be milked out, and ſet in a glaſs in the ſun, it will grow into a clear maſs, not unlike to an oriental
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:57430:86"/>pearl; as alſo, if the courſes appear about the 40th. day after the Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The right cheek is redder,<note place="margin">Fourthly.</note> and the whole colour of the face better, neither is ſhe ſo heavy as otherwiſe; and the firſt ſtirring on the right ſide is the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day, and that ſtrongly too; and the right foot moves firſt in walking; and in ariſing from a ſeat, the right foot is firſt apt to bear up the body. The pulſe is more frequent on the right ſide than on the left.<note place="margin">Fifthly.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Signs of a Female.</note>Now, the ſigns of a female are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; and theſe are moſt commonly the ſigns. The firſt motion after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception is ſelt the 90th. day,<note place="margin">The 90th. day.</note> and that firſt in the left ſide.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Females are born with more ſickneſs; the thighs and privities ſwell, the colour is paler, the appetite ſtronger, and yet apt to loath that which is contrary to it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Courſes appear about the 30th. day after conception.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Youth bring males.</note>Fourthly, the age of the woman is very conſiderable; for the younger
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:57430:86"/>women moſt commonly bring males, by reaſon of their greater heat in the womb: And the more aged, females,<note place="margin">Aged, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males.</note> by reaſon of the defect of heat contracted in the matrix, by their age; and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males are more often generated by ſuch Patents that are more cold and moiſt by nature, and of ſeed that is too moiſt, cold, and liquid.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Philadel.</hi> Since you have given ſuch a character of the ſigns of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> and the diſtinction of Sexes; let me know by what ſigns you appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the infant to be well, and thrive in the womb, or not.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer: Sign of the infants thriving</note>
               <hi>Eutrapelia,</hi> I ſhall, Sir. And firſt, if it be well, the breaſts will be hard; but if otherwiſe, they will be flaccid, and a wateriſh humor will flow out of them (like to milk) of its own accord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if the courſes flow too often out of the womb in the time of child-bearing, it is an argument of an unhealthy child. And, moreover, the fatteſt women commonly bring forth the weakeſt inſants.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:57430:87"/>
            <p>Thirdly, if a woman bring twins, the one a male, the other a female, there is great danger of the female, becauſe they are nouriſhed by a different ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the womb: but if they be both females, there is the leſs danger.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if the child be gotten in the time of the monethly terms, they are mix'd with untoward humors; from whence it is experienced that many le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous infants are begotten.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Superfaeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> what. <hi>Ariſtot.</hi> Hiſt. Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal. <hi>Lib. 7. C.</hi> 4.</note> Fifthly, if there be <hi>ſuperfaetation,</hi> the laſt conception ſeldom liveth. Now, <hi>ſuperfaetation</hi> is, when a woman having once conceived, conceiveth again after a certain time, which ſometimes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth. Hence the Poets feign <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi> to be twins by <hi>Alc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maena</hi> the wife of <hi>Amphitrio;</hi> the firſt, begotten by <hi>Amphitrio;</hi> but the laſt, <hi>viz. Hercules,</hi> begotten by <hi>Jupiter.</hi> But this by the way, although more inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might be alledged nearer home.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Signs of a dead child.</note>Sixthly, if a Dropſie overtake the praegnant woman, and that her noſe, cars, and lips look red; it is a ſign of a dead child.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:57430:87"/>
            <p>Seventhly, if the infant come forth after the ninth moneth, 'tis oftentimes very weak.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, if a virgin conceive before her firſt flowers, it proves a luſty and perfect child.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, all theſe things praemiſed,<note place="margin">Note.</note> Midwives alſo uſually obſerve, that as many knots as they find in the navil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of an infant, ſo many males, they ſay, ſhe will have. But, ſo much for Conception. Tell me now ſomewhat of Abortion, with its Cauſes and Signs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="section">
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:57430:88"/>
            <head>SECT. XXVIII. <hi>Of Abortion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> Tell me,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> Mrs. <hi>Eutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelia,</hi> what is that which you call <hi>Abortion,</hi> or miſcarrying?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> It is, to bring forth an untime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly birth; which may proceed from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers cauſes, and thoſe either internal or external.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from internal cauſes, as, from the infant it ſelf;<note place="margin">Internal <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yledons,</hi> what.</note> as, when the <hi>Cotyle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons</hi> (that is, the mouths of the veſſels ending in the womb through vvhich the blood is conveyed into the vvomb from all parts of the body) are ſo infirm, that thoſe veſſels, by reaſon of their rarity and vveakneſs, are ſooner broken; and ſo of conſequence, and Abortion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if the tunicles (that is, the <hi>ſecundine</hi>) vvherein the infant is vvrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, be ſo vveak, that it break, and the humor contained therein flovv out, by vvhich the matrix is ſlippery &amp; vveak,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:57430:88"/>and the infant being deſtitute of thoſe humors, faileth. And alſo, vvhen vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent moiſtures flovv forth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the expulſive faculty of the vvomb.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the third cauſe is, vvhen the Woman is ſo vveak and conſuming in her ſelf, that ſhe vvithdravvs the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment from the infant; inſomuch, that it hath neither matter to grovv by, nor to generate the parts and members of it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly; the fourth cauſe may be the wideneſs of the orifice of the womb, and its overmuch moyſture, and an evil temperature of qualities and ventoſities included in the womb; as alſo Ulcers and Apoſtemations in the womb, beſides other diſtempers; As are, too many Courſes, too great a Flux of blood,<note place="margin">A caution to the Iriſh, where theſe diſtempers are Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demical, and Spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radical.</note> too great a Looſeneſs of the belly, or, too great Coſtiveneſs; a <hi>Tenaſmus,</hi> (called commonly a Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,) a Cough, a conſtant Sneezing, and all things that ſhake the body too much; and laſtly, any acute ſickneſs,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:57430:89"/>which doth ſo afflict the womans body, that, by them, the infant is deprived of its nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Queſt. The exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal cauſes of Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Anſwer.</note>
               <hi>Philadel.</hi> Now then, Mrs. pray in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form me vvhat are the external cauſes of Abortion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Sir, the external cauſes are many. As, firſt, to fall, to run, to leap, to ride, to exerciſe too immoderately, and to be ſmitten vvith ſtrokes.</p>
            <p>Again, too much cold, and too great heat; for over-much cold killeth the child, and too great heat intercepts the air from the infant, and ſo ſuffocateth it in the womb; and this may be done by hot baths, if women uſe them in the firſt moneths after their conception.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Stinking ſmells, as the ſnuff of a candle, or lamp, newly extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, an abſurd appetite, and manner of eating and drinking; as, to cat ſalt, coals, dirt, &amp;c. by which, either ill humors, or a dangerous thirſt are procured.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, too great hunger; for by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:57430:89"/>fulneſs the infant is ſooner ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focated, the paſſages appointed for nouriſhment being the ſooner ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, immoderate exerciſe and labours, overmuch ſleep, and a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual lazineſs, unſeaſonable and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable watchings; beſides other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents: As, ſudden fury, great wrath, over-much fear and ſorrow, ſudden joy, and a dull appetite, longing for that which is not to be had, unſatiable copulation and luſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr. Philadel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> You have now diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the cauſes of Abortion. What, I pray, (Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia</hi>) are the ſigns of Abortion?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer. Sings.</note> The ſigns of Abortion are twofold. Firſt, before conception in thoſe that uſe to miſcarry; as, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous moyſture, ſudden and unuſual fatneſs againſt nature, which was wont to be of ſlender and lean conſtitution, or, which are ever pained about the loyns and kidneys, or fall ſuddenly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other dangerous diſeaſes.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:57430:90"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Signs of Abortion.</note>Secondly, the ſigns of Abortion af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conception are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> when the breaſts that at firſt were turgid and hard, are obſerved to grow flaccid and ſoft of a ſudden; if there be too great a flux, and a continual flowing, of the terms. Moreover, if there be horrors, colds, pains in the head, or a ſwimming there be in the eyes; theſe be ſure ſigns of Abortion.</p>
            <p>Dr. But,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> what are the ſigns of a dead child?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer. Of a dead child.</note>
               <hi>Eutrap.</hi> Where the child is dead, Sir, there is no motion perceived; when the eyes of the woman ſink, when her colour is turned into a tawny white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when there are great pains about the navil and loyns, when, by reaſon of the lower parts being compreſſed, there happeneth a Strangury, a<note n="*" place="margin">A Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Again, when the ears, the lips, the top of the noſtrils are taken with a pale coldneſs, and the face ſwells, and the belly (though it ſinketh not yet) groweth ſoft; ſo that lying to either ſide by the touch there may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:57430:90"/>a hard maſs;<note place="margin">Stinking breath a ſign that the child beginneth to putrifie.</note> as alſo ſtinking breath, an argument that the infant doth begin to putrifie. Theſe are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſigns of a dead child. The cure whereof I leave to the care of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Phyſitians and Chirurgeons.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="section">
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:57430:91"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXIX.</hi> Rules for Child-bearing Women.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>EUtrap.</hi> According to your promiſe, I beſeech you, Doctor, lay me down ſome Rules to be obſerved by Child-bearing women.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Philadel.</hi> Good Midwife, I ſhall, and that very neceſſary ones too, that ſhe may know how to go on ſafely through (by Gods bleſſing) to the laſt hour, or by neglecting them, may make her delivery the harder: and I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them under ten heads.</p>
            <p>Firſt, let her be chearful; (not break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf with mourning, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful anxiety) for this doth exhilarate the infant,<note place="margin">Res ſex non natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rales.</note> and ſtirs up all the faculties, and confirms it in its parts and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let her avoid all violent motion, and abſtain from all hard la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, not riſing up too haſtily, not leaping, running, dancing, riding; not
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:57430:91"/>lacing her ſelf too ſtreight, or carrying too heavy a burden; but ſurely ſleep is very fit for her.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, let her beware of ſharp and cold winds, of exceſſive hear, anger, perturbations of the mind, affrights &amp; terrors, over-much venery, and of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancy of eating and drinking.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, let the diet of breeding women be frugal, and moderate, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from groſs meats hard of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion; let her eat eggs, chickens, land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fowl, birds of the mountains, &amp;c. va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of broths, grewels, panadoes, mutton, veal, lamb, kid, rabbets; ſhe may uſe in her meats nutmeg and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon; ſhe may drink wine mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, in the firſt four moneths let her open no vein, uſe no cupping or ſcarrifications, fontanells, nor uſe any pills, or other Phyſick, without the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of a prudent Phyſitian; for in theſe moneths the ligaments of the child are very tender, ſoft, and feeble; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eaſier deſtroyed, and the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment kept from him.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:57430:92"/>
            <p>Sixthly, if it ſhall happen that the woman be too coſtive (by which many miſcarry) let her boyl ſpinage,<note place="margin">Againſt Coſtive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuce, well buttered, with ſalt and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, or wine; which, if they will not move the belly,<note place="margin">Suppoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> let her uſe ſuppoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, with honey, and the yelk of an egg, or of <hi>Castile</hi>-ſoap: and if theſe common things will not do, let her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe with an expert Phyſitian.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, if it happen that ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive with grievous ſymptoms,<note place="margin">Symptoms.</note> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conception is troubled with fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, let her take this Cordial follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Take of Sorrel-water, and red-Roſe-water, of each one ounce; of Cinamon-water one ounce;<note place="margin">Againſt fainting.</note> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Christi</hi> pearled, (called in the Shops <hi>Saccharum tabulatum &amp; perlatum ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex</hi>) half an ounce, or as much <hi>Diamar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariton:</hi> this may be taken as need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, if ſhe fear that ſhe may come too ſoon (that is, before her time) as in the ſeventh moneth, or ſome other unſcaſonable time, and feels throws, as
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:57430:92"/>of child-bearing, occaſioned by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate exerciſe; too great coſtive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, from a Fever, or ſome other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe;<note place="margin">A ſuffumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</note> Let her ſit over a ſuffumigation of Frankincenſe; for that contributes no ſmall ſtrength both to the matrix, and to the infant alſo.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, if ſhe nauſeate her meat, ſhe may uſe a plaiſter of Maſtich to her ſtomack, and take this following Cordial every morning, faſting, to ſtrengthen her ſtomack.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial.</note>Take ſyrup of Pomegranates one ounce and half; of Moſch and Amber-greece, of each two grains; of <hi>Lignum</hi> Aloes finely powdered, one ſcruple; of Cinamon half a ſcruple; the water of Sorrel three ounces; let theſe be mingled, and drank off blood-warm.<note place="margin">Againſt terms it Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, if, whilſt ſhe goeth with child, ſhe perceiveth her terms, let her eat milk made boyle with red-hot ſteel, and in that let Plantain and Comfrey be boyled. But, in all theſe caſes, let her adviſe with learned Phyſitians, which will direct them with medicines,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:57430:93"/>and advice from time to time. I ſhall now treat of ſome few diſtempers inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to child-bed; and leave you ſome choice Remedies in the following Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; and then wind up all.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="section">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:57430:93"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXX.</hi> Of the Retention of the <hi>Lochia,</hi> (in Child-bed) known by the name of Courſes (though im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly ſo called) and of their immoderate Flux.</head>
            <p>THE retention or ſuppreſſion of the <hi>Lochia</hi> in Child-bed,<note place="margin">Hippoc. lib. de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura pueri.</note> by the conſent of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> as well as other Learned Doctors; (to which daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience may be added;) brings the greateſt inconveniences to women,<note place="margin">Purgations of women in Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, <hi>Hippo. ibid.</hi>
               </note> and often death it ſelf. I ſhall therefore in this Section treat of the purgations of women in Child-bed, which <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> determines to be at the moſt but 40 daies,<note place="margin">By the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical Law 33 daies was in caſe of a male, <hi>Levit.</hi> cha. 12. verſe 4. and for a female, 66 daies, ve. 5.</note> if the women bring forth a female; and 30 daies to a male. But withal ſaith, that a woman is paſſed all danger after 20 daies purgation: Now, if women be not ſufficiently purged in Child-bed, either it cauſeth a great
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:57430:94"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">A ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, hot and red.</note>Phlegmon in the womb, by reaſon of the inflammation of the blood; or elſe thoſe <hi>lochia</hi> being carried to ſome higher part, bring dangerous affects to the part that receiveth them; as, Squi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancies, Pleuriſies, Fevers, Frenzie, Nauſeouſneſs, Unquietneſs, Dropſies, and what not?<note place="margin">Cauſe.</note> The cauſe of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is (generally) cold, by reaſon of the ambient air which the woman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth in her delivery;<note place="margin">Ambient air.</note> (perhaps through the improvidency of Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives; who, moſt commonly, take more care of the child than of the woman;) or elſe, by reaſon that the woman may be delivered in ſome cold, moiſt room; which cold ſuddenly ruſhing into the inward parts of the womb, ſuddenly ſtoppeth them.<note place="margin">See Sect. the fifth.</note> Therefore Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives muſt not only be very wary in this caſe, as hath been already hinted in the latter end of the fifth Section, (to which I refer you) but alſo proceed to the Cure.<note place="margin">The Cure. A Glyſter.</note> Firſt then, this Clyſter may be given: Take of the roots of Marſhmallows,<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ga &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> long &amp; round Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:57430:94"/>of white Lillies, of each half an ounce; of the leaves of Mallows, Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litory of the wall, Mercury, and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, of each half a handful; of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momel flowers, Melilot flowers, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der flowers, each two<note n="*" place="margin">A pugill is as much as may be held be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the thumb and two fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note> pugills; of the ſeeds of Dill, Foenugreek, and Seſeli, of each two drachms; let theſe be boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſpring-water, till a third part be conſumed; ſtrain it, and to ten ounces of the ſtraining, diſſolve the yelk of two eggs; of <hi>Sal-Gemm,</hi> and unguent <hi>de Arthanita,</hi> each one drachm; oyle of Dill, and of Bayes, each half an ounce; of theſe make a Glyſter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A bagg.</note>You may alſo make a bagg trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, (whereof you ſee a deſcription, with its uſe, in the xxvth. Section) in which you may quilt theſe herbs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, being groſly bruiſed and poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>Take of the roots of long and round Birth-wort, of Gentian, Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica, Bryonie,<note n="*" place="margin">Cyclami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> Sowbread, of the herbs of Mugwort, Balm, Savin, Orgamint, and Calamint, of each one handful; of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:57430:95"/>the flowers of Chamemile,<note place="margin">Ingredients for the bagg.</note> Tanſy, and Elder, each half a handful; of the ſeeds of Dill, Caraway, Anniſeeds, and Seſeleos, each one drachm: Theſe being maſh'd, and pounded, and quilted into a bagg big enough to cover the lower part of her belly and privities, and well ſecured with ſtrings, muſt be boyled in ſpring-water, and applyed warm;<note place="margin">Two baggs beſt to be applyed, the one hot, whilſt the other groweth cold.</note> but it were better to have two bags, to apply as they grow cold. The belly, hips, and thighs, which, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the conſent of parts, muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ſympathize with great pains, may be anointed with this ointment: Take of the oyle of Chamomile,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Lumbrico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Catello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Hiperico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> Dill, and of the oyle of Eggs, oyle of Worms whelps, St. <hi>John</hi>'s-wort; with theſe mixed anoint the parts aboveſaid warm. At night you may let this Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lep be given: take of the waters of Balm,<note place="margin">A Julep.</note> and Mugwort, of each one ounce; of the water of Cinamon diſtilled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wine, one ounce; Confection of Alkermes, half a drachm; of <hi>Lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> two grains; of ſyrup of Poppy,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:57430:95"/>half an ounce: the bagg may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed as need ſhall require, warming it in the liquor in which it was firſt boyled; the next day you may repeat both the Glyſter and the bagg, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect good ſucceſs: After which, if the woman be plethorick,<note place="margin">A Purge.</note> you may purge her with <hi>Manna,</hi> and ſyrup of Roſes, in broth, and this may be given after ſeven daies lying in. I come now to ſpeak ſomewhat of the immoderate flowing of them,<note place="margin">Immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Lochia.</hi>
               </note> which muſt be conſidered as well as being ſtop'd, there being dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in either: for 'tis well obſerved by <hi>Hippocrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hipp. Aph. <hi>51.</hi> Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Omne ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur in vitium. <hi>The Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi>
               </note> that every thing wherein is exceſs, is an enemie to nature: Therefore let us endeavour to ſtop them in their over-much flowing, with a very great caution, leſt by ſtopping them all together, there follow worſe effects. It happens many times, that both after the birth, and miſcarrying, that there floweth out ſuch a quantity of blood, by reaſon of the eruption or apertion of the veſſels, immoderately, or, by reaſon of the great fervor of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:57430:96"/>the blood proceeding from the uſe of over-hot Remedies in laborious births. To remedy them; Then,</p>
            <p>Firſt, uſe ſuch alimentary food, as may incraſſate and thicken the blood;<note place="margin">Cure by Diet.</note> as, Panadoes, Gellies, Rice, in the broth of Calves-feet, Pears, boyled Quince, and Roaſt-meats whereon the juice of Pomegranates have been ſprinkled, yelks of eggs.<note place="margin">Drink.</note> Their drink may be red Wine mix'd with water, wherein ſteel hath been quenched; then the blood may be drawn by revulſion to the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per parts, either by Phlebotomy, or Cupping-glaſſes under the papps, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Stupps dipp'd in [vinegar &amp; water,] applyed to the loynes with an ointment.</note>The whole belly muſt be ſwathed; there may be ſtupps dipp'd in Oxycrat, and applied to the loyns; after which, take of <hi>Unguentum Comitiſſae</hi> two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; of juice of Plantane one ounce, beaten well together: theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not hard to be gotten, I tender to you; but when they will not be ſtop'd by theſe means, 'twere beſt to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Learned Phyſitians for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="31" type="section">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:57430:96"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXXI.</hi> Of the Fever of Milk.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>EUtrap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> You have already diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the danger of the <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine</hi> being left behind, and the <hi>Lochia</hi> ſtop'd: now, Sir, be pleaſed to let me know what may be the reaſon why women fall into Fevers, although nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Lochia</hi> be ſtop'd, nor any part of the <hi>ſecundine</hi> left behind?</p>
            <p>I ſhall, good Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> for thoſe Fevers that accompany women in Child-bed are never without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; of which I ſhall give you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; ſome of them being critical, others putrid, others ſymptomatical. I call that a Fever critical, which I call a Fever of milk; ſo called,<note place="margin">Fever of milk, what, and when.</note> becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the third or fourth day after child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, the milk begins to have a more plentyful recourſe to the breaſts, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is carried with ſome force, by reaſon of the motion and agitation of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:57430:97"/>the blood converted into milk for the nouriſhment of the infant: although this kind of Fever doth not happen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all women, neither doth it uſually continue above three or four daies,<note place="margin">Febris Ephemera.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſſolved by ſweating, and needs little other remedies (moſt commonly,) if the <hi>Lochia</hi> be not ſtop'd.<note place="margin">The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Cautions in driving back milk to ſoon.</note> The cauſes may be, the driving back of the milk too ſoon (which ought not to be) which doth over-run the blood, and ſettle there; or elſe, becauſe that the breſts being filled with milk, and diſtended very big and full, the veſſels for blood are ſo compreſſed, that they will not admit of that blood that floweth thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; inſomuch, that the blood being hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in its circulation, beginneth to rage over the whole maſs of blood, whoſe ſpirits being inordinately ſtirred up, and confounded, take heat, and begin to boyle, and leaving the womb, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the whole maſs of blood, and ſo perhaps turn into putrid and malign Fevers;<note place="margin">Putrid.</note> amongſt which, many happen to be ſymptomatical;<note place="margin">Sympto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical.</note> as, a Squi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:57430:97"/>a Pleuriſie,<note n="*" place="margin">Peripneu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia.</note> an inflammation of the lungs, a Dyſenterie, and the Small-pox or Meaſels: but theſe ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomatical Fevers being from the ſame fountain of<note n="*" place="margin">A Bloody Flux. Blood out of its veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</note>
               <hi>extravaſat</hi> blood, (which moſt times turns into Apoſtemations, Tumors, and Inflammations, if not prevented) will bear the ſame Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of cure, with reſpect to the parts they invade: but to begin with critical Fevers. The cure of which conſiſts, firſt,<note place="margin">Cure of critical Fevers.</note> in an exact obſervation of diet, that the impurities of the blood, and the due purgation of the humors, the evil affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the womb may be corrected, and the ſtrength impaired may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored.<note place="margin">Strength, how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. Diet.</note> Wherefore, let her diet be Oatmeal-caudles, with white-Wine, and all mix'd, wherein a top of Baulm, Speremints, Mugwort, or Orgamint may be boyled; as alſo, Panadoes, and Water-grewels, &amp;c. with theſe ſhe muſt be fed for a week at the leaſt, by often ſupping; forbearing nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are ſtronger and ſolid; as alſo all manner of fleſh, which are
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:57430:98"/>uſually the cauſe of thoſe Fevers;<note place="margin">Eating fleſh in Child-bed the cauſe of Fevers.</note> for women in Child-bed muſt be dealt with not only like thoſe that are grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly wounded, but like thoſe whoſe maſs of blood is diſturbed, and ſo apt to be incenſed with the leaſt flame.</p>
            <p>The next care conducing to the cure is,<note place="margin">Cold.</note> to prevent outward colds, (as hath been formerly obſerved,<note place="margin">Section 5th. and 31th.</note> in the 5th. and 31th. Sections.)</p>
            <p>Wherefore, I would adviſe, that women be kept in their beds for five daies at the leaſt after their delivery. I know 'tis uſual for them to riſe at three daies end; but this to be ſure, the longer women contein themſelves in their bed, the more ſecure they are from danger. The third obſervation is, that by a gentle proritation of the blood, the <hi>Lochia</hi> be continued; and to this end Midwives uſually give <hi>Sperma Ceti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Uſual me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines.</note> Iriſh ſlatt poudered, or Saffron tinged in white-Wine, or Marrigold-flowers in poſſet-drink. If the belly be coſtive, it may be moved either with a Violet confect made for a ſuppoſitory,<note place="margin">Suppoſ to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> or ſome
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:57430:98"/>gentle emollient Glyſter, (avoiding ſtronger Glyſters.) Where there hath been vomitings, thirſt, and want of ſleep, occaſioned by the great pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations of the blood, and ſtopping of the<note n="*" place="margin">Lochia.</note>
               <hi>Lochia;</hi> I have known <hi>Laudanum</hi> mix'd with Saffron, each two grains, and given in poſſet with good ſucceſs. Inſtead of cooling Juleps,<note place="margin">Julep.</note> you may uſe this rather, of which you may give three or four ſpoonfuls often times in a day: take Pennyroyal-water, Balm-water, each three ounces;<note n="*" place="margin">Aqua Bryoniae compoſita.</note> Hyſterical-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, two ounces; Tincture of Saffron, two drachms; a<note n="*" place="margin">20 grains</note> Scruple of <hi>Caſtoreum</hi> tyed in a fine rag, and hanged in the glaſs. Here alſo may be uſed Bezoar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical medicines, ſuch as provoke ſweat; but theſe, as alſo the cure of thoſe ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomatical Fevers before hinted, I leave to be conſidered of by Learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, to whom it is ſafeſt to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in ſuch caſes of danger.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="32" type="section">
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:57430:99"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXXII. Dr. Philadelphos.</hi> I ſhall, Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia,</hi> in this Section, afford you a Miſcellany of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, ſuch as are moſt uſeful for you to have with you; and conclude all.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>Philadel.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oyles.</note> you may remember, in the latter end of the 4th. Section, I gave you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thoſe things that a Midwife ought to be furniſhed withal, wherein mention was made of oyles, which uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally are,<note place="margin">Difficult Births.</note> oyle of Lillies, of ſweet Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, or Chamomile, mixed. I ſhall offer you one ointment, in hard and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Births: take of new butter not ſalted, and waſhed in Mugwort-water, two ounces; the<note n="*" place="margin">The mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilage is the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of ſeeds and fruits boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to gelly, and ſtrein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> Mucilages of Line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, Figs, and the ſeeds of Marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallows, extracted out in the water of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:57430:99"/>Savine, of each half an ounce; oyle of Lillies, half an ounce; make a lini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with which frequently anoint the neck of the womb; you may uſe alſo ſneezing-powder, made thus:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Errhine,</hi> or Sneezing-powder.</note> Take long Pepper, <hi>Caſtoreum,</hi> Betony, white Hellebore, ſweet Marjoram, Cloves, each a drachm, made into very ſmall powder, and kept for uſe; which may be ſnuff'd up into the noſtrils, to cauſe ſneezing; or, of white Hellebore,<note place="margin">An other.</note> and <hi>Caſtoreum,</hi> powdered; this potion alſo may be given. Take of Cinamon,<note place="margin">A Potion.</note> of the bark of <hi>Caſſia fistula,</hi> of Dittany, of each one drachm and half; of white Sugar, as much as all; let all theſe be made into a fine powder, and of it drink two drachms, in that poſſet wherein Lineſeed hath been boyled, or elſe in white-Wine. Or this,<note place="margin">An other.</note> Take of <hi>Caſſia fiſtula</hi> powdered, two drachms; Red<note n="*" place="margin">A ſort of red Peaſe, <hi>Ciceri ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri.</hi>
               </note> Cicers, half a handful, let them boyl in white-Wine and water, of each as much as will ſuffice, adding at the length two drachms of Savine, ſtrein it, and adde to it half a drachm of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:57430:100"/>and ſix grains of Saffron, and make a potion. Or this,</p>
            <p>Take Aegrimony,<note place="margin">Another.</note> Betony, Vervain, each a handful; Confection of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kermes,<note place="margin">A ſcruple is twenty grains.</note> a ſcruple and half; Sugar and Cinamon as much as will ſuffice to aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matize it, the herbs being firſt boyled in poſſet-brink. I ſhall give one gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Cordial water, which I ſhall not only commend to Midwives to have ever by them, but alſo to other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen; it being a general Cordial water againſt moſt diſtempers. Thus then; Take Baulm, Betony, Pellitory of the wall,<note place="margin">A general Cordial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water.</note> ſweet Marjoram, Cowſlip flowers, of the flowers of Roſemary and Sage, each a great handful; of the ſeed of <hi>Annis,</hi> ſweet Fennel, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riander, Caraway and Gromel, of each half an ounce; of Cinamon, Lico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, and Nutmeg, all bruiſed, each one ounce; of Juniper-berries, one ounce and half; let the herbs be ſhred, and infuſed in a gallon of Brandy in an earthen pot well leaded, for the ſpace of a fortnight; afterwards ſtrein it,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:57430:100"/>and put in twelve ounces of Loaf-ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,<note place="margin">Note, that a gallon of Brandy added to the ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtrein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, makes as good water as the former, if ordered ſo.</note> and of Musk and Ambergreece, each two grains, tyed up in ſilk, and hang'd in the glaſs: you may put in another gallon of Brandy, after the firſt is ſtreined.</p>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Againſt immoderate flux of the Courſes.</head>
               <p>Take of the roots of Tormentill, two drachms; Bole-armeniack the beſt, one drachm; the ſpecies of Hyacinth,<note place="margin">Powder.</note> half a drachm, all made into fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: of which, take half a drachm once in three hours, in this following Julep.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Julep.</note>Take of the<note n="a" place="margin">Reſ. Aq. Scordii compoſit.</note> compound water of <hi>Scordium,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Dracon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii.</note> Dragon-water, &amp;<note n="c" place="margin">Ulmariae.</note> Mead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweet, of each three ounces; of<note n="d" place="margin">Aceti Theriaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</note> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle-vinegar, an ounce; ſyrup of Coral, two ounces; burnt Harts-horn, half a drachm; make a Julep.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:57430:101"/>
               <head>To facilitate the Birth, drive out the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundine, falſe Conception, and dead Child.</head>
               <p>Take of the Trochiſchs of Myrrh, one ſcruple; of Borax half a ſcruple; of Saffron three grains; make a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of theſe, and take them in white-Wine, or the decoction of Mugwort in Poſſet-ale; after which, drink a draught of the ſame Poſſet, with ſome few drops of oyle of Amber, or oyle of Juniper-berries infuſed in it. Or this,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A Poſſet.</note>Take Mother of Time, one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; of Pellitory of the wall, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momel-flowers, of each half a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; of Fennel-ſeeds, and Licoras, each half an ounce; Figs ſlit n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. ſix; boyl theſe in three pints of Poſſet-ale, till one pint be conſumed; then ſttein it, and of this drink a good draught thrice in a day. The next Receipt ſhall be directed to the falſe Conception, and dead Child. As thus; Take <hi>Styrax
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:57430:101"/>Calamita,</hi> Myrrh, Cinamon, <hi>Caſſia lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">From the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the flowers, expell a dead child, and falſe Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> of each half an ounce; Mummy, two drachms; Saffron, half a drachm; make all theſe into fine powder: this may be taken in white-Wine, a drachm at a time, for a week together, or more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To prevent Abortion.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>Sanguis Draconis,</hi> Red Coral, both made into powder,<note place="margin">A powder to be taken in broth, &amp;c.</note> of each one drachm; of Ambergreece, three grains; of Bezoar ſtone, four grains; of this powder, a ſcruple at a time may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, either in Mace-ale, or Broth, or Poſſet-drink, wherein Plantane, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey, Knot-graſs, Bramble-leaves, Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winckle, with ſome Cinamon, have boyled. Or this,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A ſecond powder,</note>Take Kermes-berries, two drachms; red Coral, and white, of each one drachm and half; of Amber, one ſcruple; make theſe into pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and put them into a Poch'd-egg, and ſup it up; do ſo till all be done. Or this,</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:57430:102"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A third powder.</note>Take Maſtich, Frankincenſe, <hi>Sang. Dracon.</hi> Myrtill-berries, Kermes-ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Bole-armeniack, each half a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and take a drachm of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and fill the hole, whence the ſtone is taken out in a Date; moyſten it in ſack, and wrap it up in a paper, and put it under hot embers to be warmed; and, let thoſe that fear Abortion, eat it often.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſme to the navil.</note>Take a hot manchet out of the oven, cutting off the cruſt, dip it in Muſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, and ſtrew it with the powder of Nutmegs and Cinamon, each as much as will ſuffice; and apply this hot to the navil of the woman.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A plaiſter from the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note>Take of Emplaſter <hi>ad Herniam, Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaris,</hi> each half an ounce; <hi>Cocci Baphici,</hi> one drachm, made into powder; Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſter of <hi>Diacalcythios,</hi> one ounce; and with as much oyle of Myrtles as will ſuffice, make a Plaiſter to be ſpread on leather, and applyed between the hips. Here may be uſed <hi>Unguentum Comitiſſae</hi> to the loins.<note place="margin">Unguent.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:57430:102"/>
               <head>Of After-pains.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cauſes of After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pains.</note>After-pains may proceed from the acrimony of the blood, being thinn and ſharp; or, from the grumous part of it, being thick, and clotted; which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture endeavouring to diſcharge it ſelf of, as to the ſetling of the womb, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth theſe pains:<note place="margin">Inflations. Ambient air.</note> As alſo Inflati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by reaſon of the ambient air, ſeems to imitate thoſe pains, with the Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, which are not only Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical, but Symptomatical; this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo uſual, few women are free from it: And,<note place="margin">Cure.</note> becauſe they often ceaſe within two or three daies, they ſeldome require a Phyſitians help. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that Julep before-mentioned in the <hi>32th.</hi> Section, is very uſeful. Or elſe,<note place="margin">The Julep in the <hi>32th.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with this * Aſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risk.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Take the inward bark of an Elm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, and burn it to aſhes; to which, adde Cinamon made into powder, ſome 10 grains of Cinamon to one drachm of the aſhes, and drink it with white-Wine. Or elſe,</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:57430:103"/>
               <p>Take of oyle of ſweet Almonds, two ounces; ſyrup of Violets, one ounce; water of Penniroyal, half an ounce, for a draught.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Potion. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pains from windineſs.</note>If the cauſe be from wind, you may give a drachm of Barberries in powder, in the water of Vervain, or Baulm.</p>
               <p>But, moſt uſually, theſe pains are eaſed by Caudles made with half white-Wine,<note place="margin">Caudles.</note> and half water, wherein Spermints, Baulm, Penniroyal, or Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort have been boyled.</p>
               <p>I will give you the form of a Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, which is not only of great uſe in the ſending forth of the <hi>ſecundine</hi> (in caſe any piece of it ſhould be left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, as ſometimes it may happen) but alſo to help nature in its work of throwing out this grumous blood; (which is the cauſe of the After-pains) And this is it;</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A Caudle, in caſe any part of the <hi>Secundine</hi> be behind.</note>Take Oatmeal, and Hempſeed, of each a ſufficient quantity, with a top of Baulm; boyl theſe in a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of white-Wine and water, of each a-like, and with the yelk of one egg, make a Caudle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:57430:103"/>
               <head>Of Convulſion-fits in infants newly born.</head>
               <p>Take the beſt Sack and Sugar mull'd, and give it the firſt thing it takes; this will diſcharge the ſtomack of that viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous flegm that ever accompanyeth infants;<note place="margin">Convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, from viſcuous phlegm poſſeſſing the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack and nerves.</note> and not only warm the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack and nerves, (for all Spaſms and Epilepſies proceed from the nerves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oppreſſed with cold, or groſs, phlegmatick humors) but prepare it for future nutriment. If theſe prevail not, uſe this enſuing Julep and Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Julep.</note>Take Black-cherry water, red-Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, and Dragon-water, of each two ounces; one top of Roſemary, of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coras, a drachm; of the flowers of<note n="o" place="margin">Flores Tiliae.</note> Linden-tree, of the Lillie of<note n="p" place="margin">Lilia Convallia.</note> Convall, of each a pugill; boyl them till a third part be conſumed, and ſweeten it with Sugar-candy; give the infant often of this, together with this Plaiſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</note>Take Mithridate, two drachms;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:57430:104"/>Saffron, one ſcruple poudred; ſpirit of Wine, ſome few drops; Capons-greaſe, as much as a ſmall nut; make a plaiſter to be ſpread upon a ſmall piece of ſcarlet, and applyed to the pit of the Stomach. And, if the child be coſtive,<note place="margin">Suppoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> put up a Mallow-ſtalk butter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or a Violet Confect, as Suppoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; this powder is good. Take<note n="n" place="margin">Rad. Paeoniae.</note> Piony-roots and ſeeds;<note n="o" place="margin">Dictamni albi.</note> Diptany; Miſleto of an Oak, of each half an ounce; of the ſeed of<note n="q" place="margin">Seminis Atriplicis.</note> Orach; of the ſcull of a man,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>p</hi> Viſci Quercini.</note> each two drachms; red Coral and Hyacinth prepared, of each a drachm and a half; of Elks-hoof prepared, half an ounce; Musk, fix grains; Leaf-gold, half a drachm; make a powder of this; give ten grains, or twenty grains in the Julep aforeſaid, in a ſpoon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Of a Diarrhaea, or a Looſeneſs in Child-bed.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Philad l.</note> A violent looſeneſs in child-bed is not without danger; to prevent which,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:57430:104"/>theſe Glyſters may be given ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>n="1"<note place="margin">Two Gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note>1. Take Rice, one drachm and half; of Cork finely grated, two drachms; Red-roſe-leaves, half a handful; ſtrein theſe, and make a Glyſter, after they have been boyled in a pint and half of milk to a pint; the things that remain may be applyed to the navil in form of a plaiſter.</p>
               <p>n="2"<note place="margin">Cataplaſm.</note>2. Take milk a quart, boyled to a pint; of <hi>Diaſcordium,</hi> half an ounce; the yelks of two eggs in form of a Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; make a Glyſter:<note place="margin">Caution.</note> but here care muſt be had, that by too aſtringent means the <hi>Lochia</hi> be not ſuppreſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Of ſore breasts in Women.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve breſts againſt the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of milk. An Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſter.</note>To preſerve the breaſts, that if they nurſe not their children, the milk of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend not, or, being extravaſate, cauſe Apoſtemations;</p>
               <p>Take Virgins wax white, four oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; <hi>Spermaceti,</hi> two ounces; of <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banum</hi> diſſolved in ſtrong vinegar, one
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:57430:105"/>ounce: Make an Emplaiſter, to be laid on the breaſts, and continued for many daies; let it be ſpread upon lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen: if the breaſts ſhould tend to break, then,<note place="margin">A Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſm, if the breaſts ſhould break, to be ſpread upon the wooll.</note> Take a Sheeps head, wooll and all, bruiſe it, and boyle it in water e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, till it be all to maſh. In the top of the ſtreined liquor of which, boyl Rice enough to make it to the conſiſtence of a Pultiſs; to which, add ſome Saffron, and apply it, and the wooll over it.<note place="margin">Clefts in the nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</note> If the nipples be ſore with fiſſures and clefts; Firſt, waſh the furr and ſtuff off from the nipples, as clean as may be; with red-Roſe-water, as hot as may be endured; Then uſe of white wax, one ounce; of <hi>Sper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maceti,</hi> half an ounce;<note place="margin">1 Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> the marrow of Staggs-bones, two ounces; oyle of St. <hi>John</hi>'s-wort, one ounce: apply this. Or,<note place="margin">2 Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Take Goats-ſuet, one ounce; oyle of the yelks of Eggs; oyle of ſweet Almonds; oyle of Henbane, and Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, by expreſſion, of each half an ounce; the fat of Geeſe, Capons, and Ducks, of each three drachms; of Litharge;
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:57430:105"/>of Silver; white Lead waſhed;<note place="margin">Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel ſtampt, and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, driveth back milk, preventeth Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note>
                  <hi>Tutia</hi> prepared; of red Lead, of each one drachm and a half; of <hi>Pompholyx;</hi> burnt Allom; white Sugar-candy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; of <hi>Olibanum,</hi> of each one drachm; of Saffron, one Scruple; of Camphire, and Opium prepared,<note place="margin">Flax card<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſmoaked over Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe, with which cover the breaſt.</note> of each half a ſcruple: mingle theſe, and with as much white wax as will ſuffice, make of theſe an Unguent.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="33" type="section">
            <pb n="140" facs="tcp:57430:106"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXXIII.</hi> Of Nurſes, and the beſt Milk.</head>
            <p>SInce the choice of a Nurſe is of ſo great a concernment;<note place="margin">Philadel.</note> (as upon which, the future being of the infant conſiſts) ſurely this,<note place="margin">Nurſes not ſluttiſh.</note> then, requires ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſerious conſiderations. For, though ſhe may have milk enough, yet perhaps not good enough; or the woman either ſluttiſh, or unhandy, or careleſs in the ſwathing and dreſſing of the child; by which many children (like new veſſels,<note place="margin">Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vabit ode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diù.</note> which will keep the ſavour of that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor they are firſt ſeaſoned withal) are ſluttiſh or ſlovenly ſo long as they live; or elſe (being abuſed at nurſe, are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtort and Ricketty; full of botches, naſty, and nauſeous to their own pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. And many, through the intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perancy of their nurſes, who, by drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to increaſe their milk (and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps make it bad enough) ſleep ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely and profoundly, that they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:57430:106"/>their nurſeries in the night,<note place="margin">Children, how over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid. Often ſleep good.</note> and the children dead by their ſides in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Therefore let Nurſes ſleep ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that they may hear the leaſt cry of the infant. But this as introductory to a larger diſcourſe and deſcription. Let the Nurſe, then, be of a middle ſtature,<note place="margin">The Nurſe deſcribed; with her Complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, her Age.</note> and good complexion; active, not fat, (and of a ſanguine complexion, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) and not in poverty; not under twenty years of age, nor above forty, but rather of twenty five, or thirty years of age, as a<note n="*" place="margin">Medio tutiſſimus ibis.</note> mean bewixt both. Let not her nipples be great, leſt it make the child of a wide mouth,<note place="margin">Her nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples not too big.</note> becauſe it cannot ſuck without the contraction of the lips together; and, leſt by forcing the tongue into too narrow a compaſs, it hinders the ſwallowing of the milk.</p>
            <p>Next, if the nipple be too ſmall,<note place="margin">Not too ſmall.</note> the child is apt to let it ſlip out of the mouth, and cannot handſomely hold it, ſo that the infant being fruſtrated of ſuck, and yet ſtill exerciſing ſucking, hurts the cheek, and attracts ſome kind of humors thither, which oftentimes
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:57430:107"/>become praeternatural tumors; and oftentimes the cheeks of the infant ſeem as if they were ſtirred out of their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Thirdly, by the conſent of all, the Nurſe muſt have a large breaſt (though ſome think that not ſo material,<note place="margin">Pectorae late jacens mammis Virgil. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retum. <hi>Great breaſts not good.</hi>
               </note> and others are of opinion that ſhe ought to have large breaſts) becauſe there is more milk collected together in great breaſts than ought; and being there, is corrupted, to the prejudice of the Nurſe. Wherefore, leſt the milk ſhould continue there too long, it is beſt to have a luſty young child to ſuck it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, or elſe to uſe ſome other way; (as,<note place="margin">Young whelps kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſucking of women.</note> by the uſe of young whelps; whom I have oftentimes ſeen dye with ſucking womens milk; ſurely the reaſon muſt be, becauſe the milk was<note n="*" place="margin">Of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> heterogene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; or elſe, becauſe grumous, and corrupted) or milked out ſome other way; eſpecially, when the Nurſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives her ſelf prejudiced by it. But it is ever beſt,<note place="margin">Plenty of milk ever beſt.</note> that ſhe abound, rather than want milk; and then in this caſe it is beſt they be big, though all Nurſes
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:57430:107"/>need not have big breaſts; for there may be as much milk, if not more, in a leſſer breſt, than in a great one. Our next enquiry will be into the manners and behaviour of a Nurſe. The beſt Nurſe then is, ſhe that is mild, chaſte,<note place="margin">The Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> ſober, courteous, chearful, lively, neat, cleanly, and handy; becauſe bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, as well as good, are ſuck'd in with the milk, and ſo radicated, that it is a hard matter to pull out the bad conditions, and leave the good behind, but that there will be a remainder of the bad conditions, perhaps ſo long as they live: wherefore, let not the Nurſe be of an angry, malepert, and ſaucy diſpoſition, ſhameleſs, ſcolding, or quarrelſome; not gluttonous, but ſo careful of her nurſery, that ſhe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eat or drink that which may be hurtful to the infant:<note place="margin">Her care in eating and drinking.</note> That ſhe do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to anger her ſelf, to grieve, or ſad her ſelf;<note place="margin">Paſſion hinders the good milk. Mirth.</note> for ſuch paſſions will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſtribute themſelves, to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the infant; than which there is nothing of more efficacy to deſtroy
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:57430:108"/>the goodneſs of the milk. Neither is it ſufficient that they abſtain from the uſe of their husbands;<note place="margin">Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from Venery not ſufficient.</note> but when they have wanton thoughts, and laſcivious minds, wholly upon Luxury and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery, they caſt off all care of their nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, and dreaming at night of that which their minds run on in the day,<note place="margin">Somnians dixit quae vigilans voluit. Terent. Comaed.</note> and by other filthy pollutions they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the milk. So alſo, by the uſe of their husbands the Courſes are ſtirred up, by which both the plenty and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of milk is derived another way; and ſo the child robbed of its nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or elſe the Nurſe conceiveth with child, and ſo the infant becometh<note n="*" place="margin">Colostra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</note> diſeaſed and Ricketty, by ſucking grumous, curdy, and unwholſome milk, and is the worſe for it during life. Therefore let all thoſe things be avoided,<note place="margin">Meats to be avoided by Nurſes.</note> that either do, or are ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to provoke luſt; as, junkets made with ſpices; alſo onions, leeks, garlick, and all ſalt meats are to be avoided: perſly,<note place="margin">Perſly, an enemy to milk.</note> and ſmallage, ſome ſay, have a peculiar malice to the increaſe of milk:
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:57430:108"/>beſides that, it doth increaſe luſt, and is an enemy to the growth of infants. Again, that Nurſe were beſt, that hath lately been brought to bed of a boy if to nurſe a boy, the milk of ſuch a Nurſe being better tempered.<note place="margin">The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of the milk of a male, and of a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male.</note> For the milk of a male child will make a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male nurſery more ſpritely, and a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Virago; and the milk of a girl will make a boy the more effeminate. As to the milk, let it be a mean,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the milk.</note> betwixt thick and thinn; which you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, by dropping it upon the thumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nails; for if it be too thinn, it will run off the ſooner; but if thicker,<note place="margin">Tryal of the milk.</note> it will ſtay the longer: let it be ſweet, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, both to the ſmell and taſte; not offending the palate with rancidneſs, ſourneſs, ſharpneſs, or ſaltneſs; or the noſtrils with any ſtrange quality. Let it be can did to the ſight,<note place="margin">By its Quality.</note> in it ſelf equal in each particles, not infeſted with brown, yellow, green, blue,<note place="margin">Colour.</note> or any other evil colour; or, as ſometimes, with various colours and ſubſtance; as, with lines, and ſtreaks upon it: but let that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:57430:109"/>milk be moſt praiſe-worthy, that makes as much curd as whey; which may be tryed by this Experiment,<note place="margin">Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
               <hi>viz,</hi> Put ſome of this milk into a glaſs, and put in ſome Myrrh, or Rennet; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtirred together, will curd, and then may the contents be ſeperated: the tryal is, that if there be moſt whey, then is the milk thinner in its ſubſtance; but if moſt of curd, 'tis thicker: yet all theſe may be corrected and amended; for that which is too thick may be mended by an extenuating diet,<note place="margin">Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives of milk too thick. Vomit.</note> and the flegmatick matter may be avoided by a vomit of Oxymel, and Exerciſe before meat, the better to conſume and atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate the thickneſs of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of milk too thinn. Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Alica.</hi>
               </note>The thinneſs of milk is amended by contrary food, ſuch as doth incraſſate it: as Formenty of Wheat, and Rice; Hogs-feet, Calves-feet, Trotters, and ſweet Wine, unleſs ſomewhat elſe be in the way to hinder it. Sometimes it happens that the milk is more tart than it ought to be:<note place="margin">Sharpneſs, &amp;c.</note> wherefore then, all diligence muſt be had to feed upon ſuch
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:57430:109"/>meats as are of the beſt juice, till that acrimony at leaſt be attempered.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Want of milk, the Cauſes.</note>Sometimes there is little or no milk in the breaſts; as after ſome ſickneſs, or notable diſtemper, now turned into a chacochymical habit, or any other of what kind ſoever, that poſſeſſeth thoſe parts, or is the morbifick cauſe: but that ſhall not be our buſineſs to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of now. Now, if theſe be not the cauſes, let the Nurſe uſe ſupping meats, as Broths, Poſſets, &amp;c. and eat plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully, and uſe frictions to her breaſts and duggs,<note place="margin">Exerciſe, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the child, good for the Nurſe. Cupping-glaſſes. Fomenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> exerciſing her hands and her arms by domeſtick Employments; or inſtead thereof, let her dance the child, by which the aliment may be recalled into thoſe parts. Sometimes cupping-glaſſes to the breaſts, with a fomenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of emollient herbs boyled in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and applyed warm, either ſponges, or wollen-clothes; after which,<note place="margin">Embroca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brocating them with oyle of Lillies. The ſeeds of Fennel, and the roots of Parſnips boyled in Barley-water,<note place="margin">What food is beſt.</note> and buttered. The broth of Hens, or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:57430:110"/>with Cinamon and Mace. Or Poch'd-eggs, with the ſeeds of <hi>Annis,</hi> and <hi>Dill;</hi> and all things elſe that are hot in the firſt and ſecond degree, are good.<note place="margin">Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms.</note> Worms, ſuch as come out of the earth, (not out of a dung-hill,) ſix or ſeven of them dried, and powdered, and drank in Barley-water ſugared, for a fortnight together: All theſe may be of good uſe in the defect of milk. But now let us ſee to the inconveniency (if there be any) in too much milk. If the milk abound too much,<note place="margin">Milk in too great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance. A Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is (though ſeldome) blameable; Then uſe the decoction of Myrtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, and red Roſes, and with clothes dipped in it, lay them on the breaſts. Or elſe clothes imbibed in Vinegar, wherein Cummin-ſeeds bruiſed have been infuſed with Myrrh and Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of too thick milk.</note>By reaſon of the thickneſs of the milk, all thoſe excrements that the child ſhould ſend forth, are intercepted; as by Stool, by Urine, &amp;c. The paſſages for tranſpiration are ſtuffed up, ſo that the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:57430:110"/>progreſs of the aliment being ſtop'd, of neceſſity the milk muſt be regurgitated, and vomited up; after which will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low much flegmatick matter, a ſure ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of crudities.<note place="margin">Cauſe of Botches, &amp;c.</note> Sometimes there will ariſe botches, and apoſtemations about the body; much matter, and ſnot, and quittor will come out of the noſe, and corners of the eyes, and eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids; and the appetite will be loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of too thin milk, the cauſe of gripings</note>Contrarily, from the thinner and ſharper ſort of milk, the belly is looſer than it ought, being troubled with pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and gripes in the belly of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant: Alſo, very angry puſtules and whelks will ariſe about the body, like the ſmall Pox; and the body groweth weak by little and little,<note place="margin">Cauſe of puſtules.</note> the infant not caring for food; for the ſtrength of the appetite will be more remiſs, by reaſon of the acrimony of that which the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant deſires; ſo that it is not much ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of that aliment which it hath; and that aliment of which it is ſenſible is naught, and vicious.</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:57430:111"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much milk</note>Now, from the over-abundance of milk, the infant oftentimes, when it ſucks, is over-whelmed, being ſo puffed up, and the belly diſtended, as if it would break; untill by much piſſing, or breaking wind, it is ſlacker. But where there is too much ſcarcity of milk,<note place="margin">Of too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle milk.</note> here the infant being altogether deſtitute of its nouriſhment, will pine away;<note place="margin">Maraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> and all the parts of the body being ſtarved, in thoſe years when it moſt wants nouriſhment, by reaſon of the vehemency of the innate heat,<note place="margin">Vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the innate heat.</note> and that habit of body (that the leaſt blaſt will puff down) which requires much, and conſtant aliment. By all which, women ought to be the more provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, leſt all theſe miſchiefs happen, (eſpecially, not to make choice of ſuch a Nurſe,<note place="margin">A good caution, not to chooſe a Nurſe in poverty. Another Nurſe to be choſen.</note> whoſe poverty muſt needs ſtarve her ſelf, and her nurſery; and if they ſhould ſo happen, to amend them, as hath been ſaid before) e're they grow incurable, and require the help of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Artificer that may cure it. Or, if the fault in the milk cannot be cured
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:57430:111"/>and amended in the Nurſe, (which ſhe hath contracted,) Then you have no more to do, but preſently to look for another Nurſe, that hath none of theſe inconveniencies; that ſo the infant may have ſuck enough, which is all it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; for want of which, you may hear ſad ejulations, crying, and weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And this may be diſcovered by their dreams,<note place="margin">Dreams.</note> as by the often motion of the lips in the cradle, as if they were ſucking when they are a ſleep.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The infant partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pates of that food which the Nurſe eats or drinks.</note>Neither is it ſtrange, that the infant ſhould be ſenſible of, and participate of whatſoever food (as meat, drink, and phyſick,) that the Nurſe taketh: which maketh our modern Phyſitians purge the Nurſe, to cure the child. And this alſo is concluded on by <hi>Hippocrates;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hippoc. Epidem, <hi>vi.</hi>
               </note> That if a woman take any purging Phyſick, ſhe purgeth her child alſo. So, <hi>Galen</hi> reports of Goats, feeding in <hi>Aſia,</hi> where Scammony did grow, did communicate a purging faculty to their milk. And ſo the milk of Aſſes, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally accounted the beſt in Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:57430:112"/>is counted better, if the Aſſe be fed with Capillary herbs, ſuch as are Maiden-hair, &amp;c. And again, when young Goats ſuck Sheeps-milk, the rough hair ſhall loſe its courſneſs, and become like a fleece of wooll: and ſo contrarily, when lambs are brought up by Goats, their wooll groweth the more hairy. If then the qualities of the milk paſs into thoſe that ſuck them,<note place="margin">Qualities of the milk paſs into thoſe that ſuck them, and ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities.</note> (as without doubt they do) it is eaſie to gather, that other impurities follow thither alſo, neither is it improbable. Surely then, we ought to take no leſs care of the Nurſe than of the child; as in her diet, exerciſe, phyſick, &amp;c. ſince, whatſoever conduceth to the benefit of the Nurſe, tends to the good and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the infant.</p>
            <p>I have been the larger in this Section of Nurſes, and Milk, becauſe tender in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants can neither make choice of their Nurſes themſelves; nor diſcover, or plead for their wants: Their own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſurely, (if they are able) both by duty, and nature, being the moſt fit to
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:57430:112"/>nurſe their own children;<note place="margin">The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Ladies, and all Mothers, fitteſt to nurſe their own chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> which the greateſt Ladies may do, with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt conveniences; by reaſon of their plenty of all things; beſides, their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance of ſervants, who can bring their nurſeries to them at all hours, be it by night or day, and take it from them again, not to diſturb their reſt: which alſo, they may intend at their own pleaſures.<note place="margin">The time of ſucking not above twelve moneths.</note> The longeſt time that a child need be ſuckled, is not to be above one year. I ſhall leave only one caution for Nurſes, and wind up this Section: and 'tis this. Let Nurſes ever milk out ſome milk e're they ſuckle the child; and after it is ſuckled,<note place="margin">Nurſes not to rock the infant too violently after ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> that they rock it not too much preſently after, leſt violent rocking diſturb the meat in the ſtomack; or the other parts draw away the milk in the ſtomack, as yet unconcocted.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="34" type="section">
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:57430:113"/>
            <head>SECT. XXXIV.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>EUtrap.</hi> Sir, I was unwilling to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt you in your diſcourſe, (it being ſo profitable) till you had done: and truly, Sir, I muſt beg your pardon, if I mind you of ſome diſtempers inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to women, and are peculiar to the womb; and though there may be more, yet I ſhall trouble you but with two: And the firſt is, concerning your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Fits of the Mother; and the ſecond, of the Falling out of the womb; which ſometimes hapneth after hard Labours, or an unskilful Midwife.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philadel.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Eutrapelia,</hi> I ſhall readily do both, as well to ſatisfie You, as other Ladies, whom I am willing to gratifie.</p>
            <div type="subsection">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:57430:113"/>
               <head>Of Suffocation of the womb, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called, Fits of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">Section, 34.</note>
               </head>
               <p>AMongſt all the fierce diſtempers that women are affected with, the ſtrangulation of the womb is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted none of the leaſt. This, by the Latines,<note place="margin">Uteri ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focatio.</note> is called the Suffocation of the womb, and ſo by the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Greeks; which we render, Hyſterical Fits, from a<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> word which ſignifieth, The womb: It is called by moſt women, The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fits, and that from another Greek<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> word, which ſignifieth, the Matrix; which is from another word, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, a Mother; becauſe women, after they have brought forth, are Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and hence, Fits of the Mother. Which is,<note place="margin">What is the ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the womb.</note> a retraction of the womb to the upper parts, making the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal parts fellow-ſufferers of the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. For although the womb may be concluded to be moved out of its place,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:57430:114"/>yet, except it be carried downwards, it never cauſeth a ſuffocation: for a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focation is nothing elſe but a defect in breathing: Therefore it is neceſſary, that the upper parts that ſerve for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration be affected,<note place="margin">The parts affected, what, and how.</note> and carried up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, by reaſon of that ſuffocation; and amongſt all, the chiefeſt are, the heart, lungs, the midriff, and the brain, to which the force of the affection cometh, <hi>viz.</hi> to the heart, by the veins and arteries, and ſo to the lungs; to the brain and midriff, by the nerves and membranes of the ſpine of the back: The cauſe is from the womb,<note place="margin">The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> which being full of ſome naughty humor, as menſtuous blood;<note place="margin">Menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood, Vitious ſeed.</note> or vitious and putrid ſeed offendeth the noble parts, with ſome ſtinking, malignant, ſharp, gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, cold vapours.<note place="margin">The ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms.</note> The ſymptoms that follow are various, either accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the greatneſs of the efficient cauſe, or the variety of ſome qualities, or natures; for ſome women are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſenſe or motion, and ſeem to have no pulſe at all, or at leaſt, that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:57430:114"/>very ſmall and weak; and ſometimes lye without any manner of breathing at all that can be perceived. Others there are, that neither want ſenſe nor motion, and ſeem not to be troubled with any paſſion of the mind; but they faint, and very hardly fetch breath: ſome alſo ſeem to have Convulſions in their joynts, as in their hands, arms, feet; but theſe generally are the ſigns of the fit at hand, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Signs of the Fit co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>in augmente.</hi>
                  </note> A dulneſs of the mind, a lazineſs, weakneſs of the thighes, paleneſs, and clammineſs about the face:<note n="b" place="margin">Signs of the Fit preſent.</note> but when the fit is come, then there cometh a<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> profound ſleep, like thoſe in an Apoplexy, or Lethargy; the mind is dotiſh, the ſenſes are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted, the voice ceaſeth, the thighes are contracted, the cheeks look red, and the face is ſwelled.<note place="margin">Signs of the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> But when the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focation declineth, a certain moyſture diſtilleth from the privities, with great rumbling and murmuring of the belly; and the womb by little and little is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxed, and ſo the ſenſe returneth. This diſeaſe is moved alſo by<note n="d" place="margin">Suppoſe of the moon.</note> courſe; as is
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:57430:115"/>the Falling-ſickneſs, and doth moſt of all infeſt young women deſirous of hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands; and that about Autumn, and the Winter: as alſo, thoſe that are childleſs, or unfruitful, or ſuch whoſe womb is chilled upon any account. This differs from<note n="*" place="margin">How it differs from a Syncope, or ſwour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> fainting Fits, in this, <hi>(viz.)</hi> In a Syncope there is no pulſe, but in the ſtrangulation of the womb, there is ever a pulſe, though ſmall, rare, weak. In fainting Fits, or ſwounings, there are cold ſweats, and paleneſs of the face; but in this the countenance is plump,<note place="margin">How from an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexy.</note> and ruddy. It differs alſo from an Apoplexy; for women that have theſe Fits have not their parts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of ſenſe and motion; and, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their ſenſes be benummed, yet, if they are pinched, or pricked, they are ſenſibly diſturbed, and will make ſigns with their hands, that they are ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; now it is clean contrary in an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexy: And again, thoſe in an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexy do ſnore, which is never ſeen in theſe hyſterick Fits.</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:57430:115"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How they differ from an Epilep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, or Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Spaſmus Cinicus.</hi> A diſtorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the mouth.</note>Laſtly, theſe Fits differ from an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilepſie, or Falling-ſickneſs, in this; that theſe parts affected are not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with Spaſmes, or Convulſions; neither do they foam at mouth, except the woman be vehemently ſuffocated; and eſpecially, when an Epilepſie is not ſtirred up out of the womb it ſelf, as oftentimes it doth happen. Having thus diſcourſed of the cauſes, ſymptoms, and ſigns, we now come to the Cure.<note place="margin">The Cure.</note> Firſt then, let the lower parts be ſtrongly rubbed with clothes, and tyed with ſtrong ligatures; as alſo, let Cupping-glaſſes,<note place="margin">Cupping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſſes, how to be uſed.</note> be applyed to the hips, groynes,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Os pubis,</hi> or <hi>Pecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> Beware the navil.</note> ſhare-bone, (but not to the navil.) Next, ſneezing is commended, (to which <hi>Hippocrates</hi> agrees.)<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Aphor. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35.</note> And, though I have given you one Receipt for a ſneezing-powder, in the beginning of the 31th. Section, which is proper not only in difficult births, but here alſo; I now will leave with you the Receipt of another powder,<note place="margin">A ſneezing powder.</note> which ſhall be this; Take white Pepper, Muſtard-ſeed, Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litory of <hi>Spain, Caſtoreum,</hi> of each a
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:57430:116"/>ſcruple; <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> and white <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebore,</hi> of each one ſcruple;<note place="margin">Twenty grains make a ſcruple.</note> and make a ſubtile powder, which may be uſed ſo long as there is no redundance of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors perceived in the head.<note place="margin">Suppoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories are good: as, Take of Agarick Troſchiſc. of the ſpecies of <hi>Hiera lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godii,</hi> of each a drachm;<note place="margin">60 Grains make a drachm.</note> of Rats-dung, Figs, Rue-leaves, and Cummin-ſeeds, all made into powder, and with honey made up into a Suppoſitory.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>Take oyle of St. <hi>Iohn</hi>'s-wort, of Orange-flowers, of Rue, of each one ounce; oyle of Mace by expreſſion, half an ounce; of a Beaſts gall dryed and powdered, ſix drachms; <hi>Venice</hi>-Treacle, half an ounce; Spiders alive, in number forty; infuſe all theſe for ten hours in a veſſel well ſtop'd on the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that it neither boyle too faſt, not evaporate too much; of this make an Ointment, with which anoint the back, and loynes, and the navil, avoiding all cold.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A fume to ſit over.</note>A Suffumigation of Nutmegs pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and ſet in a cloſe-ſtool to burn,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:57430:116"/>receiving the ſmoak by ſitting over it, is excellent.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Stinking things to ſmell to.</note>Stinking things are ever beſt to ſmell to, ſuch as are Partridge-feathers, old Leather, Brimſtone, burnt all; <hi>Aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foetida, Castoreum, Galbanum,</hi> Rue, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxed with Vinegar: Contrarily, all ſweet things are proper to be tyed to the thighes in a bag, but not ſmell'd to.<note place="margin">Sweet things beſt to be tyed to the thighes.</note> The ſcrapings of Goats-horns, and <hi>Aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foetida,</hi> mixed, and burnt, is excellent.</p>
               <p>Take <hi>Aſſafoetida</hi> diſſolved in diſtilled vinegar, of <hi>Castor</hi> prepared into pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,<note place="margin">Pills.</note> of each a ſcruple; <hi>Laudanum</hi> two grains, made into ſix Pills, and taken juſt before the Fit.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if theſe Fits proceed from the ſtoppage of the flowers, thoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines muſt be given proper to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them; but if from the retention of the ſeed,<note place="margin">Quod ſi ex retento ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niat, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerem nffectae mulieri praeſtnntius auxilium quam viri ſui frequeates amplexus. <hi>Hieronymus</hi> Pulverinus, Cap. XCI. de Strangulatione U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri.</note> then let nature here be their beſt director; except they could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue the authority of * Learned Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, with whom, let them adviſ.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="35" type="section">
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:57430:117"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. XXXV.</hi> Of the coming forth of the womb.</head>
            <p>IN the laſt Section, Miſtriſs, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed how the womb might be moveable upwards, yea, &amp; from ſide to ſide. I now come to ſpeak of its mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion downwards, which ſometimes is ſo low, that it cometh forth, and is to be ſeen outwardly; and that which hangs out doth appear like a ſoft,<note place="margin">The ſigns. <hi>Scrotum.</hi>
               </note> and round tumor, and like the Teſticles of a man; but the pain and the heat poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the privities, and bottom of the belly; and the urine, diſtilling by ſome and ſome, vexeth the privities. The cauſes may be many; as,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note>Firſt, when a woman, from on high, falleth upon her hips, thoſe skins and membranes which ſupport the womb, and tye it to the neighbouring parts, being broken.</p>
            <p>The ſecond cauſe is, by extraction of the <hi>Secundine,</hi> as hath been formerly
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:57430:117"/>ſet forth, in the 26th. Section &amp; that through the unskilfulneſs of the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife.</p>
            <p>The third Cauſe is, by a ſudden and immoderate flux of blood; as is uſually in Abortions, as hath been ſhewed in the 5th. Section.</p>
            <p>The fourth Cauſe is, by an artificial extraction of a dead child, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much holding the breath, to blow; or carrying of too great a weight.</p>
            <p>The fifth is, oftentimes, through over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much humors, and the defluxions of them; and often bearing of children; which makes thoſe Appendices, to which the womb depends, relaxed, and looſed.</p>
            <p>The ſixth and laſt is, through ſome vehement paſſion of the mind, being af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with the ſudden tydings of the loſs of children, incurſions of enemies, dangerous Sea voyages; and ſometimes from neither of theſe,<note place="margin">Old age.</note> but from old age it ſelf, or much weakneſs. But now, as to the Cure; in which, obſerve theſe Prognoſticks by the way;<note place="margin">Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks.</note> That when
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:57430:118"/>this affection is new, the womb is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reduced to its proper place; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right put up, it continues there, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the prime of age; and may both conceive, and bring forth again; but in riper years, it becomes contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; it may be put up truly, but upon the leaſt occaſion ſlips out again. And in ſhort, this; All fallings down of the womb, which are not, and cannot be cured by proper means, ſhew that the <hi>Appendices</hi> (as aforeſaid) are either lax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or broken.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Cure.</note>The Cure is, Firſt, to provide Gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to be adminiſtred, by which the ſtrait gut may be diſcharged of groſs and hard excrements, and the bladder of its urine, by ſome pipe fitted for the purpoſe; for ſometimes it happens, that the womb being in a ſtreight betwixt thoſe two,<note place="margin">Naſcim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus &amp; Urinam.</note> cannot be reduced into its proper place. The firſt may be done by Glyſters, the latter with a pipe put up in the neck of the bladder;<note place="margin">Fiſtula urinaria.</note> which done, the womb may be put up by this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing method. Let the Patient lye
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:57430:118"/>with her face upwards, her hamms bent backwards, and thighes ſpread abroad; after which, foment it with the deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; of Beets, Mallows, Marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallows, Lineſeed, and Foenugreek,<note place="margin">A fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> made in ſpring-water. Then make a pledget of wooll wrap'd up in a linnen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag, to the proportion of the privy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; which being dipped in the juice of <hi>Acatia</hi> and <hi>Hypociſtis,</hi> diſſolved in red Wine, apply it to the womb;<note place="margin">To be bought at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries.</note> and ſo without violence preſs up all that which is come forth: After which, foment the whole<note n="*" place="margin">The ſhare-bone. Another fomenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
               <hi>Pecten</hi> with this fomentation. Take red Wine a quart, red Roſe-leaves, Bramble-leaves, Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, Myrtle-berries, Shepherds-purſe, Hagtaper, Horſe-tail, and Comfrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roots, applyed with ſponges; uſing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward the oyles of Maſtich and Myrtles to the place, and <hi>Unguentum Comitiſſae</hi> to anoint the Reins. Now, becauſe the main of our drift is to cure the falling out of the womb upon difficult births; adde this method to the former. Firſt, purge her with one
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:57430:119"/>drachm of <hi>Pulvis ſennae compoſitus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Purge to be bought at the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> given in broth, or Mace-ale, twice or thrice: then, Take the leaves of Plantain, of Withy, of Medlars, of the Oake, of Sloes, of red Brambles, of red Roſes, of each a handful; of the roots of Tormentill, Comfrey, and Biſtort, of<note n="*" place="margin">Balau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia.</note> Pomegranat-flowers, of Cypreſs-nuts, of each an ounce; of the ſeeds of Anniſe, two ounces: let theſe be groſly bruiſed, and ſewed up in a bag;<note place="margin">A bag uſed.</note> (of which you have a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription in the 24th. Section of this Book.) Boyle theſe in Smiths water, ſuch as they uſe to quench iron, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it warm four times a day, wearing it continually, well truſt up.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Si quid novisti rectius iſtis,<note place="margin">Horat.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Candidus imperti; ſi non, his utere mecum.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:119"/>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:120"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Tomkyns.</signed>
               <dateline>Ex Aed. <hi>Lamb.</hi> 
                  <date>Maii ult. <hi>1671.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57430:120"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
